<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>QITI on QUANTUM INFORMATION WITH TRAPPED IONS</title>
    <link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/tags/qiti/</link>
    <description>Recent content in QITI on QUANTUM INFORMATION WITH TRAPPED IONS</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 08 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/tags/qiti/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Reprogrammable and high-precision holographic optical addressing of trapped ions for scalable quantum control</title>
      <link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2021-shih-dmd-paper/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2021-shih-dmd-paper/</guid>
      <description>We demonstrate programmable, holographic optical addressing of trapped Yb+ at λ=369 nm. Using the ion as a sensor, we characterize the total optical aberrations in the entire beam path. We then compensate for the aberration by feeding back onto the hologram, such that the residual aberration at the ion is about λ/20, which is smaller than specifications for individual commercial optic.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Programmable Quantum Simulations of Spin Systems with Trapped Ions</title>
      <link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2020-programmable-quantum-simulations-of-spin-systems-with-trapped-ions/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2020-programmable-quantum-simulations-of-spin-systems-with-trapped-ions/</guid>
      <description>This is a comprehensive review article on trapped-ion quantum simulation of spin systems, written jointly with colleagues from Univ. of Maryland, UCLA, Tsinghua Univ., Colorado School of Mines, Middlebury College, Rice Univ., Indiana Univ., Univ. of Waterloo, and UC Berkeley. The article should be accessible to a beginning graduate student. We give an overview of quantum simulation of non-trivial spin Hamiltonians generated by programmable interactions between trapped ion spins, adiabatic and dynamical evolution, ground state spin order and propagation of correlations in a many-body system.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Manipulating phonons of a trapped-ion system using optical tweezers</title>
      <link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2021-teoh-manipulating-phonons-of-a-trapped-ion-system-using-optical-tweezers/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2021-teoh-manipulating-phonons-of-a-trapped-ion-system-using-optical-tweezers/</guid>
      <description>Conventional radio-frequency ion traps provide limited controls over the confining potential. In this manuscript, we theoretically and numerically investigate a hybrid trapping architecture by incorporating optical tweezers (laser beams tightly focused on individual ions) in a conventional trap. The local control over the potential would offer many capabilities - such as engineering a target set of phonon modes, fixing the motional de-coupling problem in a multi-species ion system, and allowing novel experiments in quantum thermodynamics.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Machine learning design of a trapped-ion quantum spin simulator</title>
      <link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2020-machine-learning-design-of-a-trapped-ion-quantum-spin-simulator/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2020-machine-learning-design-of-a-trapped-ion-quantum-spin-simulator/</guid>
      <description>Trapped ion quantum simulators can in principle simulate an arbitrarily connected spin model. This requires precise programming of the ions with laser beams. In this paper, we numerically show that modern machine learning methods can be employed to program a trapped ion quantum simulator to simulate spin Hamiltonians on an arbitrary lattice geometry.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dynamical Hamiltonian engineering of 2D rectangular lattices in a one-dimensional ion chain</title>
      <link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2019-dynamic-hamiltonian-engineering-of-2d-rectangular-lattices-in-a-one-dimensional-ion-chain/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2019-dynamic-hamiltonian-engineering-of-2d-rectangular-lattices-in-a-one-dimensional-ion-chain/</guid>
      <description>In this publication, we theoretically and numerically demonstrate a powerful analog-digital hybrid quantum simulation protocol that can be used to simulate spin-dynamics on a two dimensional lattice using a linear chain of ions. The simulation protocol makes use of native long range interactions between trapped ion spins, that are then digitally modified to achieve the target spin-spin interaction graph.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Single-Atom Heat Machines Enabled by Energy Quantization</title>
      <link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2018-single-atom-heat-machines-enabled-by-energy-quantization/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2018-single-atom-heat-machines-enabled-by-energy-quantization/</guid>
      <description>Quantization of energy is a quintessential characteristic of quantum systems. Here we analyze its effects on the operation of Otto cycle heat machines and show that energy quantization alone may alter and increase machine performance in terms of output power, efficiency, and even operation mode. Our results demonstrate that quantum thermodynamics enable the realization of classically inconceivable Otto machines, such as those with an incompressible working fluid.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>