<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Home on QUANTUM INFORMATION WITH TRAPPED IONS</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/</link><description>Recent content in Home on QUANTUM INFORMATION WITH TRAPPED IONS</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 00:13:00 -0400</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>10 Sep 2025 - Ali defends his MSc thesis!</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20250910_ali_msc_defense/</link><pubDate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 00:13:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20250910_ali_msc_defense/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Congratulations to &lt;a href="https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/../members/Ali-Mustafa-Khatai/"&gt;Ali Mustafa Khatai&lt;/a&gt;

 for successfully defending his MSc thesis titled &amp;ldquo;Vacuum assembly, atomic source development and micromotion studies for a trapped Ba+ based quantum processor&amp;rdquo;! Check it out on UWSpace.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>10 Sep 2025 - paper on Optical Field Characterization with Ions is now up on Arxiv!</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20250910_kotibhaskar_optical_field_characterization/</link><pubDate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20250910_kotibhaskar_optical_field_characterization/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Our paper on characterizing optical fields using ions is &lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.07214" target="_blank"&gt;now available&lt;/a&gt;

 on the Arxiv! This is an experimental work from the QSim project that shows how ions can not only be used as a platform for quantum information processing, but also to calibrate beams in high-NA systems.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Optical field characterization at the fundamental limit of spatial resolution with a trapped ion</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2025_kotibhaskar_optical_field_characterization/</link><pubDate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2025_kotibhaskar_optical_field_characterization/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt; Optical systems capable of generating fields with sub-wavelength spatial features have become standard in science and engineering research and industry. Pertinent examples include atom- and ion-based quantum computers and optical lithography setups. So far, no tools exist to characterize such fields - both intensity and polarization - at sub-wavelength length scales. We use a single trapped atomic ion, confined to approximately 40 nm X 40 nm X 180 nm to sense a laser light field at a wavelength of 370 nm. With its spatial extent smaller than the absorption cross-section of a resonant detector, the ion-sensor operates at the fundamental limit of spatial resolution. Our technique relies on developing an analytical model of the ion-light interaction and using the model to extract the intensity and polarization. An important insight provided in this work is also that the inverse of this model can be learned, in a restricted sense, on a deep neural network, speeding up the intensity and polarization readout by five orders of magnitude. This speed-up makes the technique field-deployable to characterize optical instruments by probing light at the sub-wavelength scale.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>3 Sep 2025 - Welcome to the new graduate students: Mu, Faizan, and Chris!</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20250903_welcome_mu_faizan_chris/</link><pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20250903_welcome_mu_faizan_chris/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;New ion trappers have joined the QITI Lab! Welcome to &lt;a href="https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/../members/Mu-Niu/"&gt;Mu Niu&lt;/a&gt;

, &lt;a href="https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/../members/Faizan-Samad/"&gt;Faizan Samad&lt;/a&gt;

, and &lt;a href="https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/../members/Chris-Graham/"&gt;Chris Graham&lt;/a&gt;

! Faizan and Chris are new MSc students. Mu is a PhD student jointly supervised by Dr. Roger Melko.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Faizan Samad</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/faizan-samad/</link><pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/faizan-samad/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;I did my BA at UC Berkeley and my MS at the University of Washington. Looking forward to being a member of the team.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Mu Niu</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/mu-niu/</link><pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/mu-niu/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Mu is a PhD student working mostly on the theory of trapped ion and quantum simulation. He enjoys reading novels, playing soccer, and board games in free time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mu is jointly supervised by Dr. Roger Melko.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Bryan McNeil</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/bryan-mcneil/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/bryan-mcneil/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Second year Mathematical Physics student, interested in quantum physics / computing research&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Dhairya Goel</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/dhairya-goel/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/dhairya-goel/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;I am Dhairya Goel, 3A Mech Eng undergrad student at Univeristy of Waterloo. I will be joining the Mechanical design team to continue progress on the project being carried out in the bloodstone lab. This will be my 5th co-op under my program.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Dr. Yi Hong Teoh</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/yi-hong-teoh/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/yi-hong-teoh/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Yi Hong was a PhD student working jointly with Prof. Roger Melko and Prof. Rajibul Islam. He works on theoretical aspects of quantum simulation including implementing machine learning methods. Previously, Yi Hong did his MSc thesis with Prof. Islam and Melko, and his PHYS 437 undergraduate thesis with Prof. Islam as well.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Riddhiman Paul</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/riddhiman-paul/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/riddhiman-paul/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;I am a Mechatronics Engineer Undergrad at the University of Waterloo. I love learning new things and hope my engineering skills match Iron Man someday.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Yuvan Sooryakumar</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/yuvan-sooryakumar/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/yuvan-sooryakumar/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m an undergraduate student studying Physics. Having previously worked on theoretical planet formation, I&amp;rsquo;ve made a wild jump to this research group where I hope to leave a mark! I love video games, walks, deep discussions, reading, music, pets, and food. I also love meeting new people, so don&amp;rsquo;t be afraid to say hi!&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>14 Aug 2025 - Shilpa defends her MSc thesis!</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20250814_shilpa_msc_defense/</link><pubDate>Thu, 14 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20250814_shilpa_msc_defense/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Congratulations to &lt;a href="https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/../members/Shilpa-Mahato/"&gt;Shilpa Mahato&lt;/a&gt;

 for successfully defending her MSc thesis titled &amp;ldquo;Mitigating Optical Crosstalk for In-Situ Mid-Circuit Measurement and Reset in a Trapped-Ion Quantum Simulator&amp;rdquo;! Check it out on UWSpace.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Shilpa Mahato</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/shilpa-mahato/</link><pubDate>Thu, 14 Aug 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/shilpa-mahato/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Shilpa is a MSc Physics student in the Department of Physics and Astronomy at the University of Waterloo. She completed her Bachelor of Technology in Engineering Physics from Indian Institute of Technology Dhanbad. She is working on Quantum Simulations Project under Dr. Rajibul&amp;rsquo;s supervision.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>12 Aug 2025 - Fabien defends his MSc thesis!</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20250812_fabien_msc_defense/</link><pubDate>Tue, 12 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20250812_fabien_msc_defense/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Congratulations to &lt;a href="https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/../members/Fabien-Lefebvre/"&gt;Fabien Lefebvre&lt;/a&gt;

 for successfully defending his MSc thesis titled &amp;ldquo;Probing Micromotion in a Multi-Segmented Blade-Style Ion Trap&amp;rdquo;! Check it out on UWSpace.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Autoregressive Generative Models for Many-body Physics</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2025-yihong-teoh-phd-thesis/</link><pubDate>Thu, 07 Aug 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2025-yihong-teoh-phd-thesis/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Many body physics, the study of emergent behavior from the microscopic interactions between countless degrees of freedom, is fundamental to our understanding of the universe. Understanding these systems enable the design and development of everything from materials, pharmaceuticals and even machine learning algorithms. However, to our knowledge, classical simulation of these systems are naturally insufficient and or inefficient.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recent developments in quantum processors herald a new age in the study of many body systems. The ability to process, extract and generalize the information from such devices is pertinent to new discoveries in the field.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Dr. Yu-Ting Chen</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/yu-ting-chen/</link><pubDate>Thu, 31 Jul 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/yu-ting-chen/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Yu-Ting Chen is a Postdoctoral Fellow in the Department of Physics and Astronomy at the University of Waterloo. Her research focuses on quantum simulations with trapped ions. She received her Ph.D. from Harvard University in the Center for Ultracold Atoms, where she developed a platform for cavity quantum electrodynamics with Rydberg atom arrays.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>25 July 2025 - Yi Hong defends his PhD thesis!</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20250725_yihong-phd_defense/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20250725_yihong-phd_defense/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Congratulations to &lt;a href="https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/yhteoh/"&gt;Dr. Yi Hong Teoh&lt;/a&gt;

 for successfully defending his PhD thesis titled &amp;ldquo;Autoregressive Generative Models for Many-body Physics&amp;rdquo;! Check it out on UWSpace.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Kyle MacRobbie</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/kyle-macrobbie/</link><pubDate>Fri, 09 May 2025 02:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/kyle-macrobbie/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;I am a Physics and Astronomy undergrad here at Waterloo. I enjoy hiking, soccer, disc golf, and amateur astronomy in my free time.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Nathan Rowe</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/nathan-rowe/</link><pubDate>Fri, 09 May 2025 01:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/nathan-rowe/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;I am an undergraduate student studying Mechatronics Engineering. I am working as a Mechanical Designer for the Summer 2025 term.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Oliva Rajguru</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/oliva-rajguru/</link><pubDate>Fri, 09 May 2025 01:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/oliva-rajguru/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;I just finished my third year in physics at the Indian Institute of Science Education and Research (IISER) Mohali, currently a USEQUIP Research Intern at the Institute for Quantum Computing at QITI Lab.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Tal Kaufman</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/tal-kaufman/</link><pubDate>Fri, 09 May 2025 01:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/tal-kaufman/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Tal Kaufman is an undergraduate student studying Mechanical Engineering at the University of Waterloo. He will be working as a part of the QSim group to make progress on the Bloodstone project.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Aryan Sood</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/aryan-sood/</link><pubDate>Fri, 09 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/aryan-sood/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Hello, I am a Aryan Sood and I&amp;rsquo;m in 2nd year Physics and Astronomy. I am a aspiring researcher that is hoping to contribute to Quantum Physics research. With my previous experience as an research assistant in ultra-fast laser optics I hope to be an asset to the the team!&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Chris Graham</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/chris-graham/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/chris-graham/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Chris completed her undergraduate degree in Physics and Astronomy at the University of Waterloo. She is excited to join the group for her MSc in Fall 2025.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Zachary Lyu</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/zachary-lyu/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/zachary-lyu/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Mingze (Zachary) Lyu is an undergraduate student currently enrolled in Honours Physics. He will be working with the QSim group as a part-time contractor, as well as conducting his PHYS 437A research project for the Fall 2024 term.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Dr. Sainath Motlakunta</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/sainath-motlakunta/</link><pubDate>Thu, 09 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/sainath-motlakunta/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Sainath was a PhD student (2018-23) in the QITI group developing a &amp;lsquo;blade&amp;rsquo; trap quantum simulator. Previously, he did his MSc thesis from the same group, focusing on analog-digital hybrid quantum simulation protocols.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Kunal Varkekar</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/kunal-varkekar/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/kunal-varkekar/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Purushottam (Kunal) Varkekar is an undergraduate student enrolled in their final year of Astrophysics. He will be working with Dr. Islam and Dr. Sabooni on a Phys 437 research project. The goal of the project is to utilize deformable optics to correct for aberrations in the light and ultimately reduce cross talk when optically addressing a trapped ion system.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Lysistrata Chin Kanellakis</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/lysistrata-chin-kanellakis/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/lysistrata-chin-kanellakis/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Hi, I am Lysistrata Chin Kanellakis and I am a third-year Mechanical Engineering student and I&amp;rsquo;m excited to join the QITI team as a Mechanical co-op student!&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Dr. Nikhil Kotibhaskar</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/nikhil-kotibhaskar/</link><pubDate>Wed, 25 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/nikhil-kotibhaskar/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Nikhil wrote his thesis on programmable XY simulations, precise optical sensing, and building a segmented &amp;lsquo;blade&amp;rsquo; ion trap for quantum simulation. Previously, he co-developed a &amp;lsquo;four-rod&amp;rsquo; ion trap for his MSc thesis in the same group. Nikhil holds an undergraduate degree in Mechatronics from Sastra University in India and worked in the ion trapping lab at the Indian Institute of Science (IISc).&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>pySLM2: A full-stack python package for holographic beam shaping</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2024-shih-a-full-stack-python-package-for-holographic-beam-shaping/</link><pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2024-shih-a-full-stack-python-package-for-holographic-beam-shaping/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt; Holographic beam shaping using spatial light modulators (SLMs) as a reprogrammable hologram
offers a powerful tool for precise and flexible optical controls. It has been adopted for a wide
range of researches, including atom trapping, optical addressing
of individual quantum objects, preparation of exotic quantum states, and multi-beam laser machining.
pySLM2 is a python package designed for holographic beam shaping applications, encompassing
hologram generation, simulation, and hardware controls.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>1 Oct 2024 - Bloodstone system traps its first ions!</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20241001_bloodstone_first_ion/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20241001_bloodstone_first_ion/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;The Bloodstone system has trapped its first ions! Shown here are a linear chain of 25 Yb ions. Longer chains of ions like these allow for larger and more powerful quantum simulations. Congratulations to everyone on the Bloodstone team for their hardwork in getting this result!&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Hin Pok Cyrus Fung</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/hin-pok-cyrus-fung/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/hin-pok-cyrus-fung/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Cyrus is a graduate student co-supervised by Dr. David Gosset. As an undergrad, Cyrus worked on his PHYS 437 undergraduate thesis with Prof. Islam on &amp;lsquo;Classical Optimization Techniques for a Trapped Ion Quantum Simulator&amp;rsquo;. Cyrus is exploring various optimization and computational techniques to solve problems related to trapped ions, including machine learning.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>9 Sep 2024 - Nikhil defends his PhD thesis!</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20240909_nikhil_graduating_phd/</link><pubDate>Mon, 09 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20240909_nikhil_graduating_phd/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Congratulations to &lt;a href="https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/../members/Nikhil-Kotibhaskar/"&gt;Dr. Nikhil Kotibhaskar&lt;/a&gt;

 for successfully defending his PhD thesis titled &amp;ldquo;Towards Large Scale Quantum Simulations with Trapped Ions: Programmable XY model, Precise Light Sensing, and Extreme High Vacuum&amp;rdquo;!&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Towards Large Scale Quantum Simulations with Trapped Ions: Programmable XY model, Precise Light Sensing, and Extreme High Vacuum</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2024-nikhil-kotibhaskar-phd-thesis/</link><pubDate>Wed, 04 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2024-nikhil-kotibhaskar-phd-thesis/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;We are currently witnessing a revolution in quantum technologies. Today&amp;rsquo;s controllable quantum devices have reached a complexity that makes it practically intractable to fully simulate their dynamics using current classical supercomputers.
Decades of fundamental research and development have led us to this point. In the coming years, billions of dollars in investments from governments and private entities are expected worldwide. Although general-purpose fault-tolerant quantum computers are expected to impact computing profoundly, today&amp;rsquo;s quantum devices are best suited for their analog quantum operation, where a well-controlled quantum simulator mimics the dynamics of the other quantum system being studied. This affords an advantage over classical simulators at the cost of a restricted set of physical phenomena that can be studied. Today&amp;rsquo;s quantum devices are already providing insights into large-scale entanglement, the underlying physics of high-temperature superconductivity, disordered quantum systems, and much more. Enhancing the capabilities of today&amp;rsquo;s analog quantum simulators requires adding more classes of interactions, reducing errors due to calibration and noise, and increasing the system size to allow larger-scale simulations.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Abeiku Darkwa</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/abeiku-darkwa/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/abeiku-darkwa/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Abeiku will be working with the QuantumIon project.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Dejan Plavsic</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/dejan-plavsic/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/dejan-plavsic/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Dejan Plavsic is a co-op student here at IQC. He will be working on the mechanical design of the trapped ion system quantum computer. He is excited to contribute to such cutting-edge research and looks forward to collaborating with others.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Gary Zhong</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/gary-zhong/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/gary-zhong/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Gary is a 4th year Mechanical Engineering student studying at the University of Waterloo. He is working with the QITI research group in the Fall 2024 term, focusing on instrumentation design. Gary enjoys exploring the outdoors as well as photography.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Sakshee Patil</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/sakshee-patil/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/sakshee-patil/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Sakshee is a graduate student who previously worked with the QSim team as a Research Assistant.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Siddharth Chawla</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/siddharth-chawla/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/siddharth-chawla/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Siddharth is an undergraduate student studying Physics and Astronomy, and will be working in the QSim group for his co-op with the group.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>03 August 2024 - paper on Preserving qubits during adjacent site measurement is now available in Nature Communications</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20240803_motlakunta_preserving_qubit_naturecomm/</link><pubDate>Sat, 03 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20240803_motlakunta_preserving_qubit_naturecomm/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Our paper on Preserving a qubit during adjacent measurements at a few micrometers distance is &lt;a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41467-024-50864-2" target="_blank"&gt;now available&lt;/a&gt;

! This is an experimental work from the QSim project.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Preserving a qubit during state-destroying operations on an adjacent qubit at a few micrometers distance</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2024-motlakunta-preserving-a-qubit-crosstalk-paper/</link><pubDate>Sat, 03 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2024-motlakunta-preserving-a-qubit-crosstalk-paper/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt; Protecting qubits from accidental measurements is essential
for controlled quantum operations, especially during state-destroying measurements
or resets on adjacent qubits, in protocols like quantum error correction.
Current methods to preserve atomic qubits against such disturbances waste coherence time,
extra qubits, and introduce additional errors. We demonstrate the feasibility of in-situ state-reset
and state-measurement of trapped ions, achieving &amp;gt;99.9% fidelity in preserving an ‘asset’ ion-qubit
while a neighboring ‘process’ qubit is reset, and &amp;gt;99.6% preservation fidelity while applying a
detection beam for 11 μs on the same neighbor at a distance of 6 μm. This is achieved through precise
wavefront control of addressing optical beams and using a single ion as both a quantum sensor for
optical aberrations and an intensity probe with &amp;gt;50 dB dynamic range. Our demonstrations advance
quantum processors, enhancing speed and capabilities for tasks like quantum simulations of
dissipation and measurement-driven phases, and implementing error correction.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Programmable XY-type couplings through parallel spin-dependent forces on the same trapped ion motional modes</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2023-kotibhaskar-xy-paper/</link><pubDate>Mon, 08 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2023-kotibhaskar-xy-paper/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt; We propose and experimentally demonstrate an analog scheme for generating XY-type (Jx XX + Jy YY) Hamiltonians on trapped ion spins with independent control over the Jx and Jy terms. The Ising-type interactions σixσjx and σiyσjy are simultaneously generated by employing two spin-dependent forces operating in parallel on the same set of normal modes. We analytically calculate the region of validity of this scheme, and provide numerical and experimental validation with 171Yb+ ions. This scheme inherits the programmability and scalability of the Ising-type interactions with trapped ions that have been explored in numerous quantum simulation experiments. Our approach extends the capabilities of existing trapped ion quantum simulators to access a large class of spin Hamiltonians relevant for exploring exotic quantum phases such as superfluidity and spin liquids.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Amber Wang</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/amber-wang/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jul 2024 21:16:17 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/amber-wang/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;In her role as IQC Research Finance Coordinator, Ms. Amber Wang is the administrative assistant for the group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://uwaterloo.ca/institute-for-quantum-computing/contacts/amber-wang" target="_blank"&gt;https://uwaterloo.ca/institute-for-quantum-computing/contacts/amber-wang&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Dr. Mahmood Sabooni</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/mahmood-sabooni/</link><pubDate>Sun, 21 Apr 2024 19:19:06 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/mahmood-sabooni/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Mahmood recently joined our team as a Lead Quantum Processor Engineer, bringing a wealth of experience from his concurrent role at OpenQuantumDesign (ODD). With a background in optical engineering, Mahmood has previously worked on cutting-edge augmented reality projects at Google, demonstrating his expertise in integrating advanced optical technologies.
Since March 2021, Mahmood has been a key member of the QuantumION project, an open-access trapped ion quantum computing facility dedicated to advancing quantum research within the scientific community. His role in this project underscores his commitment to pushing the boundaries of quantum technology.
As an experimental AMO (Atomic, Molecular, and Optical) physicist, Mahmood has made significant contributions to the field of ultracold neutral atoms. At the UQML lab within the Institute for Quantum Computing (IQC), he played a pivotal role in developing exotic quantum systems by working with strongly interacting ultracold quantum matter and light. His work on Rydberg-dressed cavity polaritons is a testament to his innovative approach in quantum system design.
Mahmood&amp;rsquo;s research at UQML focused on employing advanced holographic imaging techniques to individually control and manipulate atoms within optical lattices. This work is crucial for precision quantum experimentation and manipulation. Additionally, he has made notable advancements in quantum memory technology, particularly through the use of naturally trapped rare-earth ions in crystals to store and retrieve quantum information.
Mahmood’s diverse experience and technical expertise will be invaluable as we advance our quantum computing initiatives and explore new frontiers in quantum research.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>19 Apr 2024 - Lewis defends his MSc thesis!</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20240419_lewis_graduating_msc/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Apr 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20240419_lewis_graduating_msc/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Congratulations to &lt;a href="https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/lewis-hahn/"&gt;Lewis Hahn&lt;/a&gt;

 for successfully defending his MSc thesis on &amp;ldquo;Developing a robust quantum simulator with trapped ions&amp;rdquo;! Lewis is continuing with the group for his PhD.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>18 Apr 2024 - Paper on preparation of microgram BaCl_2 Ablation Targets published</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20240206_greenberg_microgram_arxiv/</link><pubDate>Thu, 18 Apr 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20240206_greenberg_microgram_arxiv/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Our paper on Microgram BaCl_2 Ablation Targets for Trapped Ion Experiments has been &lt;a href="https://pubs.aip.org/aip/rsi/article-abstract/95/4/045117/3283252/Microgram-BaCl2-ablation-targets-for-trapped-ion?redirectedFrom=fulltext" target="_blank"&gt;published&lt;/a&gt;

 in &lt;em&gt;Review of Scientific Instruments&lt;/em&gt;! This is an experimental work from the QuantumIon project.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Microgram BaCl_2 Ablation Targets for Trapped Ion Experiments</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2024-greenberg-microgram-ablation-paper/</link><pubDate>Thu, 18 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2024-greenberg-microgram-ablation-paper/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt; Trapped ions for quantum information processing has been an area of intense study due to the extraordinarily high
fidelity operations that have been reported experimentally. Specifically, barium trapped ions have been shown to have
exceptional state-preparation and measurement (SPAM) fidelities. The 133Ba+ (I=1/2) isotope in particular is a promising candidate
for large-scale quantum computing experiments. However, a major pitfall with this isotope is that it is radioactive and
is thus generally used in microgram quantities to satisfy safety regulations. We describe a new method for creating microgram
barium chloride (BaCl_2) ablation targets for use in trapped ion experiments and compare our procedure to previous methods. We outline
two recipes for fabrication of ablation targets that increase the production of neutral atoms for isotope-selective loading of barium ions.
We show that heat-treatment of the ablation targets greatly increases the consistency at which neutral atoms can be produced
and we characterize the uniformity of these targets using trap-independent techniques such as energy dispersive x-ray spectroscopy (EDS)
and neutral fluorescence collection. Our comparison between fabrication techniques and demonstration of consistent neutral fluorescence
paves a path towards reliable loading of 133Ba+ in surface traps and opens opportunities for scalable quantum computing with this isotope.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Investigations of 2D ion crystals in a hybrid optical cavity trap for quantum information processing</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2023-sun-2d-ions/</link><pubDate>Thu, 21 Mar 2024 20:00:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2023-sun-2d-ions/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt; We numerically investigate a hybrid trapping architecture for 2D ion crystals using static electrode voltages and
optical cavity fields for in-plane and out-of-plane confinements, respectively. By studying the stability of 2D crystals against
2D-3D structural phase transitions, we identify the necessary trapping parameters for ytterbium ions. Multiple equilibrium
configurations for 2D crystals are possible, and we analyze their stability by estimating potential barriers between them.
We find that scattering to anti-trapping states limits the trapping lifetime, which is consistent with recent experiments employing
other optical trapping architectures. These 2D ion crystals offer an excellent platform for quantum simulation of frustrated spin systems,
benefiting from their 2D triangular lattice structure and phonon-mediated spin-spin interactions. Quantum information processing with tens
of ions is feasible in this scheme with current technologies.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>21 March 2024 - paper on 2D ion crystals in a hybrid optical cavity trap published</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20240321_sun_2d_published/</link><pubDate>Thu, 21 Mar 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20240321_sun_2d_published/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Our paper investigating 2D ion crystals in a hybrid optical cavity trap has been &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1103/PhysRevA.109.032426" target="_blank"&gt;published&lt;/a&gt;

 in &lt;em&gt;PRA&lt;/em&gt;! This is a theoretical and numerical work.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Gail Bender</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/gail-bender/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Mar 2024 21:16:17 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/gail-bender/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;In her role as IQC Research Finance Coordinator, Ms. Gail Bender is the administrative assistant for the group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://uwaterloo.ca/institute-for-quantum-computing/contacts/gail-bender" target="_blank"&gt;https://uwaterloo.ca/institute-for-quantum-computing/contacts/gail-bender&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Optimization of the Optical Infrastructure and Trapping Potential for a Quantum Processor Based on Trapped Barium Ions</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2024-xinghe-tan-msc-thesis/</link><pubDate>Fri, 02 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2024-xinghe-tan-msc-thesis/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Trapped ion quantum computers represent a cutting-edge quantum computing platform, keeping the highest reported state preparation and measurement fidelity of 99.97%. Recently, barium ion has emerged as the research interest of several teams due to its exceptional characteristics, including visible and inferred state transition frequencies, long-lived metastable states, and a simple hyperfine structure. Our research group aims to demonstrate trapping 16 133Ba+ ions on a micro-fabricated surface trap and build a quantum computing platform. In the long run, we intend to open access to this platform for the academic community to use. This project is named the QuantumIon project. The project started in 2019, just before the global pandemic. During the pandemic, the QuantumION team did not have the lab space and the components to prototype and benchmark subsystems in parallel with system design. Instead, the team designed the entire system on computers during the pandemic. I joined the QuantumION team in 2022 and performed the system assembly, validation and optimization when the pandemic restrictions were lifted. In this thesis, I describe the optimization of the optical system for delivering laser beams to the ions and the validation of a 0.6 NA imaging system that will be used to observe the ion fluorescence as a means of measuring its quantum state. While benchmarking the optical systems, I found that the performance of the components deviated from their ideal specifications, such as insertion loss. Therefore, I had to modify the system design to ensure the optical systems functioned in practice. In addition, I conducted a feasibility study on delivering an ablation laser via multimode fiber and simulated a trapping potential on the surface trap that achieved approximately even spacing for 12 out of the 16 trapped ions.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>12 Jan 2024 - Hawking defends his MSc thesis!</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20240112_hawking_graduating_msc/</link><pubDate>Fri, 12 Jan 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20240112_hawking_graduating_msc/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Congratulations to &lt;a href="https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/Xinghe-tan/"&gt;Hawking Tan&lt;/a&gt;

 for successfully defending his MSc thesis on &amp;ldquo;Optimization of the Optical Infrastructure and Trapping Potential for a Quantum Processor Based on Trapped Barium Ions&amp;rdquo;! Hawking is continuing with the group for his PhD.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Dr. Chung-You (Gilbert) Shih</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/chung-you-shih/</link><pubDate>Tue, 09 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/chung-you-shih/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Chung-You (Gilbert) did his PhD in the QITI group (2019-23), working on individual optical addressing of trapped ions. Previously, he did his MSc research on holographic beam shaping for quantum simulation in the same group.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Towards Pulsed Telecom Laser Ablation Loading for an Ytterbium Ion Trap</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2023-monica-zhu-msc-thesis/</link><pubDate>Mon, 23 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2023-monica-zhu-msc-thesis/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Trapped ion system is a promising platform for quantum computing, with long qubit coherence, high gate and measurement fidelities. To harness the full potential of the trapped ion system, it is imperative to employ an efficient ion loading scheme. While the conventional oven loading method has its drawbacks, such as slow loading time, resource wastage, and potential contamination that can compromise system longevity and introduce decoherence, the pulsed laser ablation loading offers a promising alternative. This method enables fast, resource efficient, and controllable generation of a neutral atomic flux. This thesis explores the development of a 1.57 μm pulsed laser ablation (PLA) loading scheme for an Ytterbium ion trap. With endeavors in theoretical simulations and experimental setups designed with a keen emphasis on laser-induced damage thresholds, we successfully generated a neutral flux from the ablation laser, acquired a comprehensive isotope spectrum, and estimated the velocity distribution in the atomic plume. A fiber-coupled ablation delivery module was also designed and proved feasible along with the main ablation experiments. This study establishes a solid groundwork for the future integration of pulsed laser ablation loading into our trap system and provides invaluable empirical insights into the use of high-power infrared (IR) pulsed lasers.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Programmable Individual Addressing and Floquet Hamiltonian Dynamics in a Trapped Ion Quantum Processor</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2023-chung-you-shih-phd-thesis/</link><pubDate>Tue, 26 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2023-chung-you-shih-phd-thesis/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Trapped ions have been gaining traction as a platform for quantum information processing (QIP) in both academia and industry over the last decade. Their long coherence time, high fidelity gate operations, and built-in all-to-all connectivity are some of the key features that make trapped ions promising. However, to unlock the full potential of the trapped ion platform, sophisticated quantum controls are required. In this thesis, we present our efforts in individual optical addressing to control an ion&amp;rsquo;s quantum state at an individual level, as well as efforts in generating complex and time-dependent Hamiltonians through arbitrary radio frequency (RF) waveform generation.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Developing a Large-Scale, Programmable Trapped Ion Quantum Simulator with In Situ Mid-Circuit Measurement and Reset</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2023-sainath-motlakunta-phd-thesis/</link><pubDate>Mon, 25 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2023-sainath-motlakunta-phd-thesis/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Quantum simulators are a valuable resource for studying complex many-body systems. With their ability to provide near-term advantages, analog quantum simulators show great promise. In this thesis, my aim is to describe the construction of a large-scale trapped-ion based analog quantum simulator with several objectives in mind: controllability, minimal external decoherence, an expandable toolkit for quantum simulations, enhanced stability through robust design practices, and pushing the boundaries of error correction. One of the techniques that significantly expands the range of simulations possible in trapped ions is site-selective mid-circuit measurements and resets. This technique enables the exploration of new classes of quantum simulations, including measurement-based phase transitions and reservoir engineering with controlled dissipation. Additionally, mid-circuit measurements play a crucial role and serve as one of the key factors in achieving error-correction in trapped ions. In this thesis, I address the challenges associated with implementing mid-circuit measurements and discuss strategies for achieving state-of-the-art fidelities in these processes within our simulator. In this thesis, I present the results demonstrating the high-fidelity preservation of an &amp;ldquo;asset&amp;rdquo; ion qubit while simultaneously resetting or measuring a neighboring &amp;ldquo;process&amp;rdquo; qubit located a few microns away. The results show that we achieve a probability of accidental measurement of the asset qubit below 1×10⁻³ while resetting the process qubit. Similarly, when applying a detection beam on the same neighboring qubit to achieve fast detection times, the probability remains below 4×10⁻³ at a distance of 6 μm, which is four times the addressing Gaussian beam waist. These low probabilities correspond to the preservation of the quantum state of the asset qubit with fidelities above 99.9% for state reset and 99.6% for state measurement. One of the many fascinating aspects of physics that can be explored through the use of site-selective mid-circuit resets is reservoir engineering. In this thesis, I discuss a protocol utilizing reservoir engineering to efficiently cool the spin state of a subsystem that is coupled to a reservoir with controlled dissipation. I demonstrate the effectiveness of this protocol through numerical simulations performed to optimize it for our experimental parameters. By leveraging the site-selective mid-circuit resets mentioned earlier, I successfully conduct a proof-of-principle dissipative many-body cooling experiment based on reservoir engineering. Through analog quantum simulation, I am able to demonstrate the lowering of energy within the system. In addition to the above explorations, another important aspect of this thesis is the description of the design, fabrication, and assembly of a large-scale trapped ion quantum simulator called the Blade trap. I discuss the essential features of this system that include accommodating a significant number of ions, extending ion lifetimes and coherence times, enabling precise control of ion spins and interactions, implementing efficient detection methods, and incorporating mid-circuit measurement capabilities. I also provide a detailed account of our approach to optimizing the design and fabrication of the blade-trap system, covering the trap itself, mechanical components, system internals, optics, and the critical ultra-high vacuum (UHV) assembly. Furthermore, comprehensive testing procedures are presented to evaluate the performance and stability of the Blade trap. I also describe the details about one of the significant challenges we faced in achieving and maintaining ultra-low pressure levels in the UHV system to ensure uninterrupted quantum simulation experiments with around 50 ions. High pressures can lead to detrimental collisions between ions and background atoms, necessitating re-trapping and introducing substantial overhead. Therefore, we aimed to achieve pressures in the range of 5×10⁻¹³ to 1×10⁻¹² mbar at room temperature, demanding meticulous optimization at the component level. Our journey to attain these pressures took approximately 2 to 3 years, complicated further by COVID-19 restrictions and equipment malfunctions. Despite the exhausting efforts, we successfully reached base pressures of less than 9×10⁻¹³ mbar in the vacuum chamber with partial internals. It is important to note that this measurement represents an upper limit due to gauge limitations.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>08 Sep 2023 - Gilbert defends his PhD thesis!</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20230908_gilbert_graduating_phd/</link><pubDate>Fri, 08 Sep 2023 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20230908_gilbert_graduating_phd/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Congratulations to &lt;a href="https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/chung-you-shih/"&gt;Dr. Chung-You Shih&lt;/a&gt;

 for successfully defending his PhD thesis!&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Taha Malik</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/taha-malik/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/taha-malik/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m a Master&amp;rsquo;s student in engineering with a passion in design. I enjoy playing basketball, photography, and working on my car!&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>15 Aug 2023 - Sainath defends his PhD thesis!</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20230815_sainath_graduating_phd/</link><pubDate>Tue, 15 Aug 2023 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20230815_sainath_graduating_phd/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Congratulations to &lt;a href="https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/Sainath-Motlakunta/"&gt;Dr. Sainath Motlakunta&lt;/a&gt;

 for successfully defending his PhD thesis, &amp;ldquo;Developing a Large-Scale, Programmable Trapped Ion Quantum Simulator with In Situ Mid-Circuit Measurement and Reset&amp;rdquo;!&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>14 Aug 2023 - Monica defends her MSc thesis!</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20230814_monica_graduating_msc/</link><pubDate>Mon, 14 Aug 2023 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20230814_monica_graduating_msc/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Congratulations to &lt;a href="https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/jingwen/"&gt;Monica&lt;/a&gt;

 for successfully defending her MSc thesis &amp;ldquo;Towards Pulsed Telecom Laser Ablation Loading for an Ytterbium Ion Trap&amp;rdquo;! Monica will be continuing with the group for her PhD.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>A guided light system for agile individual addressing of Ba+ qubits with 1E-4 level intensity crosstalk</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2023-binai-motlagh2023-a-guided-light-system/</link><pubDate>Thu, 27 Jul 2023 20:00:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2023-binai-motlagh2023-a-guided-light-system/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt; Trapped ions are one of the leading platforms for quantum information processing, exhibiting the highest gate and measurement fidelities of all contending hardware. In order to realize a universal quantum computer with trapped ions, independent and parallel control over the state of each qubit is necessary. The manipulation of individual qubit states in an ion chain via stimulated Raman transitions generally requires light focused on individual ions. In this manuscript, we present a novel, guided-light individual addressing system for hyperfine Ba+ qubits. The system takes advantage of laser-written waveguide technology, enabled by the atomic structure of Ba+, allowing the use of visible light to drive Raman transitions. Such waveguides define the spatial mode of light, suppressing aberrations that would have otherwise accumulated in a free-space optics set up. As a result, we demonstrate a nearest neighbour relative intensity crosstalk on the order of 10&lt;sup&gt;−4&lt;/sup&gt;, without any active aberration compensation. This is comparable to or better than other previous demonstrations of individual addressing. At the same time, our modular approach provides independent and agile control over the amplitude, frequency, and phase of each channel; combining the strengths of previous implementations.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>27 July 2023 - paper on individual addressing with Barium qubits published</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20230727_binai_motlagh_guided_light_published/</link><pubDate>Thu, 27 Jul 2023 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20230727_binai_motlagh_guided_light_published/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Our paper on a guided light system for individual addressing of Ba+ qubits with 1E-4 level intensity crosstalk has been &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1088/2058-9565/ace6cb" target="_blank"&gt;published&lt;/a&gt;

 in &lt;em&gt;Quantum Science and Technology&lt;/em&gt;! This is an experimental work from the QuantumIon project.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>11 July 2023 - paper on XY interactions through parallel spin-dependent forces on the same motional modes is uploaded to Arxiv</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20230711_kotibhaskar_xy_arxiv/</link><pubDate>Tue, 11 Jul 2023 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20230711_kotibhaskar_xy_arxiv/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Our paper on Programmable XY-type couplings through parallel spin-dependent forces on the same trapped ion motional modes is &lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.04922" target="_blank"&gt;now available&lt;/a&gt;

 on &lt;em&gt;Arxiv&lt;/em&gt;! This is an experimental work from the QSim project.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>01 Jul 2023 - tenured and promoted</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20230701_rajibul_tenure/</link><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jul 2023 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20230701_rajibul_tenure/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Rajibul is promoted to associate professor with tenure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks to all the present and past &lt;a href="https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/"&gt;members&lt;/a&gt;

 of the team whose hard work and dedication made this possible!&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>12 June 2023 - new paper on Long-Range XY Model for Quantum State Transfer and Optimal Spatial Search</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20230612_lewis_bose_xy_published/</link><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jun 2023 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20230612_lewis_bose_xy_published/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Our paper on Long-Range XY Model for Quantum State Transfer and Optimal Spatial Search has been &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1088/2058-9565/acd953" target="_blank"&gt;published&lt;/a&gt;

 in &lt;em&gt;Quantum Science and Technology&lt;/em&gt;! This is a theoretical work.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Ion Trap Long-Range XY Model for Quantum State Transfer and Optimal Spatial Search</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2022-lewis-bose-ion-trap-long-range-xy-model-for-quantum-state-transfer-and-optimal-spatial/</link><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2022-lewis-bose-ion-trap-long-range-xy-model-for-quantum-state-transfer-and-optimal-spatial/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt; Linear ion trap chains are a promising platform for quantum computation and simulation. The XY
model with long-range interactions can be implemented with a single side-band Mølmer-Sørensen
scheme, giving interactions that decay as 1/r^α
, where α parameterises the interaction range. Lower
α leads to longer range interactions, allowing faster long-range gate operations for quantum computing. However, decreasing α causes an increased generation of coherent phonons and appears to
dephase the effective XY interaction model. We characterise and show how to correct for this effect
completely, allowing lower α interactions to be coherently implemented. Ion trap chains are thus
shown to be a viable platform for spatial quantum search in optimal O(√N) time, for N ions. Finally, we introduce a O(√N) quantum state transfer protocol, with a qubit encoding that maintains a high fidelity&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Leo Xing</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/leo-xing/</link><pubDate>Sun, 30 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/leo-xing/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Leo was an undergraduate mechantronics Co-op student who worked as a mechanical designer in Dr. Islam&amp;rsquo;s group after his Mechatronics Eng. 2A term. Leo worked on a system to stabilize our ion imaging objective lenses.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Mustafa Syed</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/mustafa-syed/</link><pubDate>Sun, 30 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/mustafa-syed/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Mustafa was a co-op student in the Department of Physics and Astronomy. Mustafa built an optical tweezer demo experiment that will be used for teaching undergrad laboratories.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Sanju Sathiyamoorthy</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/sanju-sathiyamoorthy/</link><pubDate>Sun, 30 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/sanju-sathiyamoorthy/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m a multi disciplinary student that is passionate about all things engineering! I love problem-solving, designing and analytical thinking.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>14 March 2023 - paper on fabrication of needle electrodes published</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20230314_kotibhaskar_needles_published/</link><pubDate>Tue, 14 Mar 2023 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20230314_kotibhaskar_needles_published/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Our paper on Fast and high-yield fabrication of axially symmetric ion-trap needle electrodes via two step electrochemical etching has been &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1063/5.0108425" target="_blank"&gt;published&lt;/a&gt;

 in &lt;em&gt;Review of Scientific Instruments&lt;/em&gt;! This is an experimental work.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Fast and high-yield fabrication of axially symmetric ion-trap needle electrodes via two step electrochemical etching</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2023-kotibhaskar-fast-and-high-yield-fabrication/</link><pubDate>Tue, 14 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2023-kotibhaskar-fast-and-high-yield-fabrication/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt; Despite the progress in building sophisticated microfabricated ion traps, Paul traps employing needle electrodes retain
their significance due to the simplicity of fabrication while producing high-quality systems suitable for quantum information processing, atomic clocks etc. For low noise operations such as minimizing ‘excess micromotion’, needles
should be geometrically straight and aligned precisely with respect to each other. Self-terminated electrochemical etching, previously employed for fabricating ion trap needle electrodes employs a sensitive and time-consuming technique
resulting in a low success rate of usable electrodes. Here we demonstrate an etching technique for quick fabrication of
straight and symmetric needles with a high success rate and a simple apparatus with reduced sensitivity to alignment
imperfections. The novelty of our technique comes from using a two-step approach employing turbulent etching for
fast shaping and slow etching/polishing for subsequent surface finish and tip cleaning. Using this technique, needle
electrodes for an ion-trap can be fabricated within a day, significantly reducing the setup time for a new apparatus. The
needles fabricated via this technique have been used in our ion-trap to achieve trapping lifetimes of several months.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Darian Mclaren</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/darian-mclaren/</link><pubDate>Thu, 08 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/darian-mclaren/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;I graduated from Brandon University with a BSc in 2019 with a double major in both mathematics and physics. After taking a year off I started my MMath degree in applied mathematics (with a focus on quantum information) in the fall of 2020.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am jointly supervised by Dr. Joel Wallman, Prof. Rajibul Islam, and Prof. Sivabal Sivaloganathan.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>On the evaluation of quantum instruments with a consideration to measurements in trapped ion systems</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2022-darian-mclaren-msc-thesis/</link><pubDate>Thu, 08 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2022-darian-mclaren-msc-thesis/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Trapped ion chains have shown promise in their application as quantum simulators.
However, the close proximity of ions in the trap leads to operations such as state detection
causing loss of coherence of other ions due to imperfect beam addressing and absorption
of scattered photons during neighbouring ion fluorescence. In the first part of my thesis I
consider a Ytterbium 171 ion trap and calculate the probability of neighbouring ion photon
absorption. I additionally show how to use the Lindblad master equation to simulate the
dynamics of an ion under an attenuated beam, and provide a review of determining the
detection fidelity through histograms of photon detection counts.
I then return to the more abstract setting of non-destructive quantum measurements,
which are instrumental for fault-tolerant quantum computers. These non-destructive quantum measurements have both a quantum and classical output and hence must be described
through a quantum instrument as opposed to the typical representation of measurements
through POVM’s. It therefore becomes necessary to develop methods for evaluating quantum instruments. In this thesis I show that the process fidelity and diamond distance as
figures of merits on unitary channels may be generalized to figures of merits on quantum
instruments. I show that these figures of merit adequately capture the errors associated to
non-destructive measurements, and they additionally provide upper and lower bounds for
each other. Several examples are also given of computing the figures of merit on quantum
instruments under various noise models.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Coherent interactions and thermometry in a trapped ion quantum simulator</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2022-anthony-vogliano-msc-thesis/</link><pubDate>Fri, 02 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2022-anthony-vogliano-msc-thesis/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Quantum simulators are useful tools to study exotic systems which may be otherwise
intractable for a traditional computer. In particular, the trapped-ion platform has been a
leading candidate for use in quantum simulation experiments because of its high fidelity
state-preparation and measurement operations and its all-to-all connectivity. The relative
difficulty of interacting with the long lived hyperfine states of 171Yb+
ions make them
excellent choices for encoding information as the isolation creates stability against a noisy
environment. Maintaining coherence for such a long time opens the door for complex
coherent interactions, which are a backbone of quantum simulation experiments. One of
the most critical coherent operations for a trapped-ion quantum simulator is the entangling
Molmer-Sørenson interaction.
Building up to the Molmer-Sørenson interaction requires fine control over not just the
state of the quantum register, but also the motional state of the ion. For this reason,
cooling to near the ground state of motion is crucial to obtaining high fidelity experiments.
Characterizing the temperature in such systems can prove challenging, requiring coherent
techniques.
In this thesis, I describe my work towards preparing a Molmer-Sørenson interaction
for a 171Yb+
trapped ion quantum simulator. I detail the methods used to bring-up the
coherent Raman interactions, and characterize the Doppler cooling and Continuous Sideband Cooling (CSBC) techniques we use, their implementations on our system, and their
limitations. I characterize the temperature of our ions before and after CSBC using coherent methods, showing a 46x improvement in the motional state population and confirming
that post-CSBC the ions are in the Lamb-Dicke regime. I also summarize my efforts in
constructing a future ”blade trap” system with enough precision in the alignment of the
electrodes to eventually enable efficient cooling. I show preliminary evidence that 5um
precision in blade position should be feasible.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Robust Optical Engineering for a Trapped Ion Quantum Computer</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2022-ali-binai-motlagh-msc-thesis/</link><pubDate>Fri, 02 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2022-ali-binai-motlagh-msc-thesis/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Trapped ions are one of the leading platforms for the implementation of quantum information processing (QIP),
exhibiting one of the highest reported quantum gate and measurement fidelities. The challenge for the platform
now is to maintain these high quality operations while expanding the system size beyond the ∼10-30 qubits that
are available in today’s devices. Currently we are near completion of the construction of our trapped ion quantum
computer that will incorporate multiple isotopes of barium as qubits/qudits. Barium has several favourable properties
that make it the ideal ion for QIP and the aim of our device in the near future is to develop this species into
the premiere ion for QIP. The device in the future is hoped to serve as a cloud based resource for the Waterloo
research community, fostering collaborations between algorithms, error correction and atomic physics researchers,
that is ultimately hoped to expedite the development of trapped ion QIP. This thesis discusses the robust optical
engineering that went into the construction of this trapped ion quantum computer. We describe the details of the
continuous wave optical subsystems used for ion initialization, cooling, and measurements of the quantum states,
including the imaging system used to collect ion fluorescence. In addition, this thesis discusses the unique individual
addressing system that we have designed and built for performing single and two-qubit gates based on Raman transitions.
With this system we attain a relative intensity crosstalk between neighbouring ions on the order of 1e−4.
This is comparable to the best currently available implementations but our system provides additional optical
frequency and phase control knobs that allow for more control over quantum simulation and computation experiments.
Finally we will discuss the trap, its associated electronics and the vacuum system that houses our ions and atomic source.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>12 Aug 2022 - Anthony defends his MSc thesis!</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20220812_anthony_graduating_msc/</link><pubDate>Fri, 12 Aug 2022 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20220812_anthony_graduating_msc/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Congratulations to &lt;a href="https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/anthony-vogliano/"&gt;Anthony&lt;/a&gt;

 for successfully defending his MSc thesis on &amp;ldquo;Coherent interactions and thermometry in a trapped ion quantum simulator!&amp;rdquo; Anthony is continuing with the group for his PhD.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>08 Aug 2022 - Ali defends his MSc thesis!</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20220808_ali_graduating_msc/</link><pubDate>Mon, 08 Aug 2022 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20220808_ali_graduating_msc/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Congratulations to &lt;a href="https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/ali-binai-motlagh/"&gt;Ali Binai-Motlagh&lt;/a&gt;

 for successfully defending his MSc thesis on optical addressing for individual Barium qubits! Ali will join Columbia University as a PhD student!&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Ali Binai-Motlagh</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/ali-binai-motlagh/</link><pubDate>Mon, 08 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/ali-binai-motlagh/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Ali worked on the QuantumION project (a collaboration with Prof. Crystal Senko&amp;rsquo;s group). His primary controbution was to develop a waveguide-based optical addressing system for individual Barium ion qubits.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Ashley Saggu</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/ashley-saggu/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/ashley-saggu/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Ashley is a second year mechanical engineering student at the University of Waterloo. This term she is working with the QITI group and is interested in using CAD software&amp;rsquo;s and mechanical drawings in a lab environment. She enjoys drawing in her free time and learning new languages.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Ryan Mark</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/ryan-mark/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/ryan-mark/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Ryan is a mechatronics engineering student studying at the University of Waterloo. He will be joining the QITI research group in the Spring 2022 term. He looks forward to bringing his experience from manufacturing and mechanical design to design the optical infrastructure for the quantum simulator. He is excited to be a part of this emerging field and contribute.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In his free time, he enjoys biking, taking photos, and camping.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Souvik Sil</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/souvik-sil/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/souvik-sil/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;I am a student at the university of waterloo, very interested in engineering and physics.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>27 June 2022 - new paper on qubit control limits imposed by laser noise</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20220627_day_laser_noise_published/</link><pubDate>Mon, 27 Jun 2022 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20220627_day_laser_noise_published/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Our paper on laser noise imposing limits on qubit control has been &lt;a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41534-022-00586-4" target="_blank"&gt;published&lt;/a&gt;

 in &lt;em&gt;npj Quantum Information&lt;/em&gt;! This is a theoretical and numerical work.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Limits on atomic qubit control from laser noise</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2021-day-limits-on-atomic-qubit-control-from-laser-noise/</link><pubDate>Mon, 27 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2021-day-limits-on-atomic-qubit-control-from-laser-noise/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;This manuscript presents a numerical analysis of the impact of laser noise on qubit operations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt; Technical noise present in laser systems can limit their ability to perform high fidelity quantum control of atomic qubits. The ultimate fidelity floor for atomic qubits driven with laser radiation is due to spontaneous emission from excited energy levels. The goal is to suppress the technical noise from the laser source to below the spontaneous emission floor such that it is no longer a limiting factor. It has been shown that the spectral structure of control noise can have a large influence on achievable control fidelities, while prior studies of laser noise contributions have been restricted to noise magnitudes. Here, we study the unique spectral structure of laser noise and introduce a new metric that determines when a stabilised laser source has been optimised for quantum control of atomic qubits. We find requirements on stabilisation bandwidths that can be orders of magnitude higher than those required to simply narrow the linewidth of a laser. We introduce a new metric, the χ-separation line, that provides a tool for the study and engineering of laser sources for quantum control of atomic qubits below the spontaneous emission floor.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Dr. Roland Hablützel</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/roland-habl%C3%BCtzel/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 May 2022 20:42:06 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/roland-habl%C3%BCtzel/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Roland joined the QITI group in 2018 to work on the design, construction and characterization of a quantum simulator of spin-lattice geometries based on trapped atomic ions. His research focuses on taking advantage of the shared motional structure of the trapped ions and the flexibility of holographic imaging to program interactions between any pair of spins.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He completed his Ph.D. in the Centre for Quantum Technologies at the National University of Singapore under the supervision of Prof. Dzmitry Matsukevich, where he studied coherent coupling of motional modes in a linear chain of three ions.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Alisa Shirkalina</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/alisa-shirkalina/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/alisa-shirkalina/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Alisa is a mechanical engineering student at the University of Waterloo. She is working with the Quantum Simulation team during the winter 2022 term, focusing on mechanical and optical design. Alisa also enjoys rock climbing, skiing, and hiking.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Frank Boal</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/frank-boal/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/frank-boal/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;My name is Frank Boal and I am a 2A Mechatronics student at UW. In my free time I play hockey goalie and am currently playing Jr. hockey locally while attending school.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Mark Wallace</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/mark-wallace/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/mark-wallace/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;After working with the QITI research group in the spring of 2021 I have nothing but positive things to say about my experience. Returning after my 3B Mechanical Engineering school term was one of the easiest choices of my University career! I am looking forward to working on the optics further with more hands on experience and seeing the things designed in terms past come to life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I love digital art and creation as well as film and photography. Material science, coding and mechanical design have been highlights from my coursework and I look forward to applying my existing knowledge while learning as much as possible!&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Stephen Del Grosso Milek</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/stephen-del-grosso-milek/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/stephen-del-grosso-milek/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m currently in my fifth co-op term, employed for the second time with QITI and the QuantumION project. I’m generally interested in the manufacturing and properties of metallic materials, as well as mechanical design techniques. In particular, I’m interested in combinations of cutting-edge machining technology and new iterative design methods to manufacture and create novel creations for fashion and industrial design sectors.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>08 Dec 2022 - Darian defends his MSc thesis!</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20221208_darian_graduating_msc/</link><pubDate>Tue, 08 Feb 2022 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20221208_darian_graduating_msc/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Congratulations to &lt;a href="https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/darian-mclaren/"&gt;Darian Mclaren&lt;/a&gt;

 for successfully defending his MSc thesis on On the evaluation of quantum
instruments with a consideration to measurements in trapped ion systems!&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>06 Jan 2022 - Zewen defends his MSc thesis!</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20220106_zewen_graduating_msc/</link><pubDate>Thu, 06 Jan 2022 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20220106_zewen_graduating_msc/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Congratulations to &lt;a href="https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/zewen-sun/"&gt;Zewen Sun&lt;/a&gt;

 for successfully defending his MSc thesis on theoretical investigations into optical trapping of ions! Zewen will next move to Max Planck Institute for a PhD in theoretical physics.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Zewen Sun</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/zewen-sun/</link><pubDate>Fri, 31 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/zewen-sun/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Zewen received his BSc degree in physics from Tianjin Normal University and Trent University via a joint program, in 2019. He joined the MSc program at Waterloo in Fall 2019. At Waterloo, Zewen&amp;rsquo;s research interest is in theoretical and numerical investigations on various aspects of light-matter interaction, especially the physics of ions trapped in optical potentials.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Besides physics, Zewen is interested in almost any field, so feel free to talk to him, even if you are not sure what to talk about.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Simulating a measurement-induced phase transition for trapped ion circuits</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2021-czichek-mpt/</link><pubDate>Fri, 03 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2021-czichek-mpt/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;In this theoretical proposal, we describe a hybrid circuit where coherent time evolution is interrupted by sparse projective measurements. A measurement-driven phase transition between volume-law and area-law entanglement is predicted at a specific rate of measurement. Proof-of-principle experiments can be performed in modern trapped ion quantum information processors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt; The rise of programmable quantum devices has motivated the exploration of circuit models which could realize novel physics. A promising candidate is a class of hybrid circuits, where entangling
unitary dynamics compete with disentangling measurements. Novel phase transitions between different
entanglement regimes have been identified in their dynamical states, with universal properties
hinting at unexplored critical phenomena. Trapped ion hardware is a leading contender for the
experimental realization of such physics, which requires not only traditional two-qubit entangling
gates, but a constant rate of local measurements accurately addressed throughout the circuit. Recent
progress in engineering high-precision optical addressing of individual ions makes preparing a
constant rate of measurements throughout a unitary circuit feasible. Using tensor network simulations,
we show that the resulting class of hybrid circuits, prepared with native gates, exhibits a
volume-law to area-law transition in the entanglement entropy. This displays universal hallmarks
of a measurement-induced phase transition. Our simulations are able to characterize the critical
exponents using circuit sizes with tens of qubits and thousands of gates. We argue that this transition
should be robust against additional sources of experimental noise expected in modern trapped
ion hardware, and will rather be limited by statistical requirements on post selection. Our work
highlights the powerful role that tensor network simulations can play in advancing the theoretical
and experimental frontiers of critical phenomena.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Gaurav Tathed</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/gaurav-ashish-tathed/</link><pubDate>Thu, 02 Dec 2021 01:42:32 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/gaurav-ashish-tathed/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Gaurav is pursuing Bachelors&amp;rsquo;s Degree in Physics and Astronomy for the University of Waterloo. In the Spring 2020 term, he was working in the QITI group as an undergraduate co-op student. Gaurav is using COMSOL software to investigate noise sources in ion-traps, in particular the thermal effect of radio-frequency voltages on the trapping apparatus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What Gaurav loves about his internship at QITI is how it allows him to learn about ion trapping, and its wide range of applications in different fields ranging from Quantum Computing to High energy physics. Other than physics, Gaurav loves to understand how things work and engineering behind it. For example, as a high school student in India, Gaurav built a CNC plotter using CD players (this project was exhibited in the Nehru Science Center, Mumbai) and an algorithm for traffic signals which uses live time traffic updates. He also likes to sketch and play tennis.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Levi Medeiros</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/levi-medeiros/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/levi-medeiros/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m a coop student working on the QuantomION team. I look forward to learning more about quantum computing and optics design.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Mariah De Torres</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/mariah-de-torres/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/mariah-de-torres/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Mariah De Torres is a Nanotechnology Engineering Undergraduate Student at the University of Waterloo. In Winter 2021, she worked for QITI as a co-op student on the QSim team to design robust optical beam delivery solutions in a trapped-ion quantum simulator. She designed CAD models for beam delivery for short and long-term stability.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Nathan Snider</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/nathan-snider/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/nathan-snider/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Nathan Snider is pursuing a Bachelor&amp;rsquo;s Degree in Mechanical Engineering at the University of Waterloo. Nathan will be working with the QuantumION optics and mechanical team during the Winter 2021 term.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Tim (Jia Hong) Li</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/tim-jia-hong-li/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/tim-jia-hong-li/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Tim is a Mechanical Engineering student at the University of Waterloo. He&amp;rsquo;s working on the QuantumION project during the Fall 2021 term, focusing on mechanical design and optical assembly. Tim likes to learn math, physics, and programming outside of class. Tim also enjoys playing the piano, biking, and photography.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Ziyan Li</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/ziyan-li/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/ziyan-li/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;My name is Jerry and I like food&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Optical Design for an Open Access Trapped Ion Quantum Processor</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2021-videnov-msc-thesis/</link><pubDate>Tue, 31 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2021-videnov-msc-thesis/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;The future of quantum information is scaling to a ever larger number of qubits. Doing so will require advances in the approach for all aspects of current experimental systems. The QuantumION project is a large step in this direction. This project will provide an open-access trapped ion quantum processor for the research community. The necessary innovations for how QuantumION will be controlled and assembled represents a paradigm shift from ad-hock disparate systems running the experiment to a well engineered, integrated, quantum platform. These innovations will require coordinated work from many contributors, and this thesis covers a few specific aspects of QuantumION to which the author has contributed.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Manipulating phonons of a trapped-ion system using optical tweezers</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2021-teoh-manipulating-phonons-of-a-trapped-ion-system-using-optical-tweezers/</link><pubDate>Thu, 19 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2021-teoh-manipulating-phonons-of-a-trapped-ion-system-using-optical-tweezers/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Conventional radio-frequency ion traps provide limited controls over the confining potential. In this manuscript, we theoretically and numerically investigate a hybrid trapping architecture by incorporating optical tweezers (laser beams tightly focused on individual ions) in a conventional trap. The local control over the potential would offer many capabilities - such as engineering a target set of phonon modes, fixing the motional de-coupling problem in a multi-species ion system, and allowing novel experiments in quantum thermodynamics. In the context of multi-species ion systems, optical tweezers would enable efficient sympathetic cooling and faster logic gates between species by taking control over the participation of ions in the collective phonon modes.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>06 Aug 2021 - Gilbert receives IQC Achievement Award!</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20210806_gilbert_iqc_achievement_award/</link><pubDate>Fri, 06 Aug 2021 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20210806_gilbert_iqc_achievement_award/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Congratulations to &lt;a href="https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/chung-you-shih/"&gt;Chung-You (Gilbert) Shih&lt;/a&gt;

, a PhD student in the group for receiving the IQC Achievement Award, 2021! The awards are given to University of Waterloo graduate students working on quantum information at the Institute for Quantum Computing (IQC), based on exceptional achievement in research. Gilbert was recognized for developing an &lt;a href="https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2021-shih-dmd-paper/"&gt;ultra-precise optical addressing system&lt;/a&gt;

 for a trapped-ion quantum simulator.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://uwaterloo.ca/graduate-studies-postdoctoral-affairs/awards/iqc-achievement-award" target="_blank"&gt;More about IQC Achievement Awards&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://uwaterloo.ca/institute-for-quantum-computing/research/awards/student-award-recipients#IQCAchievement" target="_blank"&gt;List of past winners&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Paige Angela Harford</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/paige-angela-harford/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/paige-angela-harford/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Paige is an undergraduate student working in the QSim group, going into her fourth year of Physics at the University of Waterloo. Throughout summer 2021, she will investigate optical table design and fabrication.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>20 Jul 2021 - Nikhil wins best presenter award at nationwide CAP congress competition!</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20210720_nikhil_cap_win/</link><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jul 2021 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20210720_nikhil_cap_win/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Congratulations to &lt;a href="members/nikhil-kotibhaskar/"&gt;Nikhil Kotibhaskar&lt;/a&gt;

, a PhD student in the group for winning the best student presenter award at the annual Congress of the Canadian Association of Physicists (CAP)! He first won the competition in the Atomic, Molecular, and Optical Physics category and then went on to win the national competition among all areas of physics. There were about 325 competitors and an 81-member judging team.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nikhil talked about our research on developing a trapped-ion quantum simulator.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Dr. Fereshteh Rajabi</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/fereshteh-rajabi/</link><pubDate>Wed, 30 Jun 2021 23:59:59 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/fereshteh-rajabi/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Fereshteh was a postdoctoral fellow, working on theoretical aspects of trapped-ion physics. She developed hybrid digital-analog quantum simulation protocols, and investigated optical trapping schemes for ions.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Programming the full stack of an open-access quantum computer</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2021-frey-quala-full-stack-programming-quantumion/</link><pubDate>Fri, 11 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2021-frey-quala-full-stack-programming-quantumion/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;This manuscript describes the full stack programming of QuantumION, an open-access, remote-controlled, trapped-ion quantum information processor for the research community, currently being developed at Waterloo. QuantumION is a joint initiative with Prof. Crystal Senko&amp;rsquo;s research group and funded by Canada First Research Excellence Fund (CFREF).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt; We present a new quantum programming language
called ‘Quala’ that enables true full-stack programming of quantum
hardware. Quala allows seamless integration of abstraction
layers such as the digital circuit layer and the analog control pulse
waveform layer. Additionally, the language supports user-issued
low-level hardware instructions like FPGA actions. Mid-circuit
measurements and branching decision logic support real-time,
adaptive programs. This flexibility allows users to write code for
everything from quantum error correction to analog quantum
simulation. The combination of a user-facing calibration database
and a powerful symbolic algebra framework provides users with
an unprecedented level of expressiveness and transparency. We
display the salient characteristics of the language structure and
describe how the accompanying compiler can translate programs
written in any abstraction layer into precisely timed hardware
commands. We intend for this language to bridge the gap
between circuit-level programming and physical operations on
real hardware while maintaining full transparency in each level
of the stack. This eliminates the need for “behind-the-scenes”
compilation and provides users with insights into the day-to-day
calibration routines.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>08 Apr 2021 - paper on holographic optical addressing of ions published</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20210408_dmd_paper/</link><pubDate>Thu, 08 Apr 2021 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20210408_dmd_paper/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Our paper on ultra-precise holographic optical addressing of ions is &lt;a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41534-021-00396-0" target="_blank"&gt;published&lt;/a&gt;

 in &lt;em&gt;npj Quantum Information&lt;/em&gt;! This is an experimental research.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Reprogrammable and high-precision holographic optical addressing of trapped ions for scalable quantum control</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2021-shih-dmd-paper/</link><pubDate>Thu, 08 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2021-shih-dmd-paper/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;We demonstrate programmable, holographic optical addressing of trapped Yb&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; at &lt;em&gt;λ&lt;/em&gt;=369 nm. Using the ion as a sensor, we characterize the total optical aberrations in the entire beam path. We then compensate for the aberration by feeding back onto the hologram, such that the residual aberration at the ion is about &lt;em&gt;λ&lt;/em&gt;/20, which is smaller than specifications for individual commercial optic. Using an iterative Fourier transform algorithm to generate the holograms, we can suppress relative intensity `crosstalk&amp;rsquo; errors to below &amp;lt; 10&lt;sup&gt;−4&lt;/sup&gt; at a few micrometers away while addressing arbitrary sets of ions. Our results are among the highest quality optical addressing of trapped ions.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Programmable Quantum Simulations of Spin Systems with Trapped Ions</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2020-programmable-quantum-simulations-of-spin-systems-with-trapped-ions/</link><pubDate>Wed, 07 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2020-programmable-quantum-simulations-of-spin-systems-with-trapped-ions/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;This is a comprehensive review article on trapped-ion quantum simulation of spin systems, written jointly with colleagues from Univ. of Maryland, UCLA, Tsinghua Univ., Colorado School of Mines, Middlebury College, Rice Univ., Indiana Univ., Univ. of Waterloo, and UC Berkeley. The article should be accessible to a beginning graduate student. We give an overview of quantum simulation of non-trivial spin Hamiltonians generated by programmable interactions between trapped ion spins, adiabatic and dynamical evolution, ground state spin order and propagation of correlations in a many-body system. We cite examples from experiments performed over the last decade with two to fifty three ion spins.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>29 Mar 2021 - Rajibul shares his views on quantum computing in NPR Podcasts (Shortwave and All Things Considered)</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20210329_npr_podcast/</link><pubDate>Mon, 29 Mar 2021 22:24:20 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20210329_npr_podcast/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Rajibul took part in a podcast on the National Public Radio (NPR) along with Emily Kwong and Geoff Brumfiel of NPR, Chris Monroe, co-founder of IonQ and Marissa Giustina, Google.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe src="https://www.npr.org/player/embed/981315128/981786876" width="100%" height="290" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" title="NPR embedded audio player"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A different version was aired on All Things Considered on 30 April 2021.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe src="https://www.npr.org/player/embed/992545143/992545204" width="100%" height="290" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" title="NPR embedded audio player"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;</description></item><item><title>04 Mar 2021 - New paper on arXiv</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20210304_paper_teoh2021_phonon/</link><pubDate>Thu, 04 Mar 2021 22:24:20 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20210304_paper_teoh2021_phonon/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Our manuscript titled &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2103.03273" target="_blank"&gt;Manipulating phonons of a trapped-ion system using optical tweezers&lt;/a&gt;

&amp;rdquo; is on arXiv! This is a theoretical and numerical research.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Austin Con</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/austin-con/</link><pubDate>Wed, 02 Dec 2020 01:42:32 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/austin-con/</guid><description/></item><item><title>12 Nov, 2020 - Nik awarded with best presentation award!</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20201112_nik_strathclyde_best_presentation/</link><pubDate>Thu, 12 Nov 2020 22:24:20 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20201112_nik_strathclyde_best_presentation/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;University of Waterloo and University of Strathclyde, Glasgow, UK hosted their first virtual research colloquium on 12 Nov, 2020. &lt;a href="https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/nikolay-videnov/"&gt;Nikolay&lt;/a&gt; presented a talk on behalf of the QuantumION project, focusing on our design for individual addressing of Barium qubits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His talk was judged to be the best UW presentation of the day! Congrats, Nik!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://uwaterloo.ca/international/news/student-wins-best-presenter-virtual-research-colloquium"&gt;UW press release&lt;a/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://uwaterloo.ca/writing-and-communication-centre/blog/post/interview-uws-award-winning-graduate-student-presenter"&gt;Interview for the Writing and Communication Centre Blog&lt;a/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>20 Oct, 2020 - Rajibul honoured with President’s Excellence in Research award!</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20201020_rajibul_presidents_research_excellence_award/</link><pubDate>Tue, 20 Oct 2020 22:24:20 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20201020_rajibul_presidents_research_excellence_award/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/rajibul-islam/"&gt;Rajibul&lt;/a&gt; received a President’s Excellence in Research award from the President and Vice-Chancellor of University of Waterloo in recognition of an Early Researcher Award from the Government of Ontario.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://uwaterloo.ca/institute-for-quantum-computing/news/iqc-faculty-honoured-presidents-excellence-research-awards"&gt;IQC press release&lt;a/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Experimental and theoretical investigations of radio-frequency and optical trapping potentials for atomic ions</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2020-sajjan-msc-thesis/</link><pubDate>Thu, 08 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2020-sajjan-msc-thesis/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Over the years, trapped ion have emerged as one of the premier candidates for universal quantum simulation due to its long coherence time, low initialization and detection errors, robust high-fidelity gate sets and fully connected yet tunable spin-graph. In this thesis we exclusively focus on the generation of the trapping potential in a four-rod trap, one of the most commonly studied ion-trapping architecture. We elaborate the fabrication of the trapping electrodes using electro-etching techniques and explore the underlying mechanism in details. We discuss how these electrodes are powered by DC and RF field to generate the confining potential responsible for trapping the ions of interest in 3D. We conclude by studying how this trapping potential can be modified by external means like using an optical tweezer. Employing such an optical tweezer we propose a new quantum-thermodynamic protocol which shall allow us to experimentally access the thermal properties of a mixed specie ion chain using a single-specie ion chain. The scheme is based on Jarzynski&amp;rsquo;s equality and obviates the need to trap dual-ionic species as far as illustrating the mechanical properties of the chain are concerned. We present results ratifying the utility of the proposal. The scheme is useful to obtain mode-specific thermal properties hitherto unexplored experimentally.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Scott Hubele</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/scott-hubele/</link><pubDate>Wed, 30 Sep 2020 21:16:47 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/scott-hubele/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Scott joined the group for the Summer of 2020 through the IQC Undergraduate Research Award. His projects include simulating photon counts from trapped ion qubits onto multiple detectors to correlate measurements and increase detection fidelity, as well as designing an imaging system which minimizes aberration. He graduated from the University of Alberta in 2020 with a major in Engineering Physics (co-op program) and a minor in Linguistics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Outside of physics, Scott enjoys studying languages, playing the piano, and travelling (but not for now).&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Akimasa Ihara</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/akimasa-ihara/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/akimasa-ihara/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Akimasa is a PhD student under Professor Rajibul Islam&amp;rsquo;s group and is working on QuantumION project. He completed his Bachelor&amp;rsquo;s at Cornell University and has worked with the Oxford Ion Trap Group in the past.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Ali Mustafa Khatai</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/ali-mustafa-khatai/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/ali-mustafa-khatai/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Ali will be joining the QuantumION team as a new Physics MSc student in fall 2023. He obtained his bachelor&amp;rsquo;s degree in Physics and Computer Science from Illinois Wesleyan University.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Dr. Akbar Jahangiri Jozani</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/akbar-jahangiri-jozani/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/akbar-jahangiri-jozani/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Dr. Akbar Jahangiri works as a Post Doc. for the Quantum ion project.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Fabien Lefebvre</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/fabien-lefebvre/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/fabien-lefebvre/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;I did my undergrad at uOttawa, and I like playing ultimate frisbee and other sports during my free time.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Jakob Devey</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/jakob-devey/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/jakob-devey/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Working on dust trap for his co-op position as a Laboratory Assistant at the University of Waterloo.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Jillian Ryan</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/jillian-ryan/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/jillian-ryan/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Jillian is a 2nd year student in the Physics and Astronomy program at the University of Waterloo. Outside of work she enjoys hiking, reading, and yoga.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Nathaniel Ho-Wah Johnston</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/nathaniel-ho-wah-johnston/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/nathaniel-ho-wah-johnston/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;As part of his co-op placement, Nathaniel will be working on designing hardware and software control for stabilizing experimental parameters such as the intensity of laser beams. He is very interested in the field control systems and is looking forward to his introduction to research on quantum computers.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Qinghao Zhang</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/qinghao-zhang/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/qinghao-zhang/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;For his PHYS 437 BSc Physics project, Qinghao is numerically investigating noise sources in trapped-ion quantum simulations.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Samuel Slavko Laketa</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/samuel-slavko-laketa/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/samuel-slavko-laketa/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;For his PHYS 437 BSc Physics project, Samuel is numerically investigating laser frequency stabilization for trapped-ion quantum information processing. In particular, his interest is in understanding the stabilization of beat-notes in the context of two-photon Raman transitions with mode-locked lasers.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Xinghe Tan</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/xinghe-tan/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/xinghe-tan/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Xinghe (Hawking) is a PhD student on the QuantumION project. He finished his MSc from the same group in Jan 2024. He completed his Bachelor&amp;rsquo;s degree at Queen&amp;rsquo;s University.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Dr. Manas Sajjan</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/manas-sajjan/</link><pubDate>Sun, 30 Aug 2020 22:50:58 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/manas-sajjan/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;I am very interested in the interplay of the quantum and statistical physics at mesoscopic and nanoscopic length scale especially emergence of thermodynamic or statistical irreversibility from reversible quantal dynamics. My PhD was in modelling quantum transport across single molecular junctions, a highly non-equilibrium phenomenon, using electronic structure and convex optimization. Currently, I am invested in exploring the rich frontiers of QI in an AMO physical platform like trapped ions. I was responsible for fabricating the trap electrodes, for making the RF resonator and associated circuitry and for designing the repumping optics all of which were essential for making the first ion-trapping apparatus in the group, a four-rod trap with which we have successfully trapped several ions. Presently I am also dabbling in theoretical proposals for testing quantum fluctuation theorems using hybrid ion traps.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Rachel DiTommaso</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/rachel-ditommaso/</link><pubDate>Sun, 30 Aug 2020 21:42:32 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/rachel-ditommaso/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Rachel is working on the QuantumION project as an undergraduate co-op student.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Michael Melvin Veenstra</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/michael-veenstra/</link><pubDate>Sun, 30 Aug 2020 21:16:47 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/michael-veenstra/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Michael is an undergraduate co-op student in the QITI lab in Spring 2020. He is in his third year of studying Mechatronics Engineering at the University of Waterloo. In the QITI lab, Michael has been working on electronics projects related to ion trapping.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Outside of work, Michael enjoys soccer, mountain biking, and hands-on projects.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>14 Aug, 2020 - Manas defends his MSc thesis!</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20200814_manas_msc_thesis_defence/</link><pubDate>Fri, 14 Aug 2020 22:24:20 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20200814_manas_msc_thesis_defence/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/manas-sajjan/"&gt;Dr. Manas Sajjan&lt;/a&gt; defends his &lt;a href="https://uwspace.uwaterloo.ca/handle/10012/16433"&gt;MSc thesis&lt;/a&gt; online! His MSc work included both theoretical and experimental aspects. On the theoretical side, Manas investigated the role of optical tweezer potentials on ions confined in a radio-frequency (RF) trap. Optical tweezers would allow for local control of the confining potential, which can be used for investigating quantum thermodynamics. On the experimental side, Manas was part of the team that built our four-rod trap. He fabricated the electrodes, built the RF resonator which powers them, and worked on optics.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Lewis Hahn</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/lewis-hahn/</link><pubDate>Mon, 03 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/lewis-hahn/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;I enjoy snowboarding any chance I can get.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Jingwen (Monica) Zhu</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/jingwen/</link><pubDate>Sun, 02 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/jingwen/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Jingwen (Monica) received her undergrad education from University of Toronto. She completed her masters on Laser ablation systems for ion loading, and now she explores Floquet systems on the Amethyst machine.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Anthony Vogliano</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/anthony-vogliano/</link><pubDate>Sat, 01 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/anthony-vogliano/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Anthony has worked extensively in QITI lab both on hardware and programming, especially on the main experimental sequences of the Amethyst system. Specific scientific interests include the interplay of coherent dynamics and dissipation, cooling and thermal behavior of many-body quantum systems, and Hamiltonian verification protocols.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anthony enjoys travelling and cooking. His special skills include hand origame, optics table yoga, and having the second longest arms in the lab. Go Bears!&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>16 July 2020 - Building a quantum simulator</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20200716_iqc_feature_video/</link><pubDate>Thu, 16 Jul 2020 22:24:20 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20200716_iqc_feature_video/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Here is a feature of our lab by IQC. The students look very happy playing with ions!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;"&gt;
 &lt;iframe allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share; fullscreen" loading="eager" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/L7nipA12EWg?autoplay=0&amp;amp;controls=1&amp;amp;end=0&amp;amp;loop=0&amp;amp;mute=0&amp;amp;start=0" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" title="YouTube video"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;</description></item><item><title>Dr. Matthew Day</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/matthew-day/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Jul 2020 20:42:06 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/matthew-day/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Since 2019, Matt has been working on QuantumION, an open-access trapped ion quantum computer. He formally joined the QITI group in 2020.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>1-5 Jun 2020 - DAMOP</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20200601_damop/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jun 2020 22:24:20 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20200601_damop/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;DAMOP (online) talks presented by Chung-You (Gilbert) Shih on individual addressing of ions and Dr. Matt Day on QuantumION. Posters were presented by Nikolay Videnov and Sainath Motlakunta.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>12 May 2020 - TUCAN meeting</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20200512_tucan/</link><pubDate>Tue, 12 May 2020 22:24:20 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20200512_tucan/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Nikhil Kotibhaskar presents a talk at (virtual) TUCAN (Toronto Area Ultracold Atom Network), organized by University of Toronto. This is the third edition of the annual meeting. McMaster University and University of Waterloo hosted the meeting in the previous two years.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Michele Roche</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/michele-roche/</link><pubDate>Sat, 02 May 2020 21:16:17 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/michele-roche/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;In her role as IQC Research Finance Coordinator, Michele is the administrative assistant for the group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://services.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/people/profile/m2roche/" target="_blank"&gt;https://services.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/people/profile/m2roche/&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Dr. K. Rajibul Islam</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/rajibul-islam/</link><pubDate>Sat, 02 May 2020 21:14:38 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/rajibul-islam/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Associate Professor, Institute for Quantum Computing and Department of Physics and Astronomy, University of Waterloo&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://uwaterloo.ca/physics-astronomy/people-profiles/k-rajibul-islam" target="_blank"&gt;UW Physics and Astronomy profile&lt;/a&gt;

, &lt;a href="https://uwaterloo.ca/institute-for-quantum-computing/profiles/kazi-rajibul-islam" target="_blank"&gt;IQC Profile&lt;/a&gt;

, &lt;a href="\Miscellaneous_docs\CV_Islam_Aug2020.pdf"&gt;CV&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Affiliate, Perimeter Institute for Theoretical Physics&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Co-founder, &lt;a href="https://openquantumdesign.org/" target="_blank"&gt;Open Quantum Design&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Co-founder and Chief Scientific Advisor, &lt;a href="https://lightflow-optics.com/" target="_blank"&gt;Lightflow Optics Inc.&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://academictree.org/physics/tree.php?pid=172624" target="_blank"&gt;Academic Tree&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Notable recognitions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fellow, American Physical Society (2024)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;VAIBHAV fellow, Department of Science and Technology, Government of India (2024 - )&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Excellence in Science Teaching Award, Faculty of Science, University of Waterloo (2024)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;President&amp;rsquo;s Excellence in Research Award, University of Waterloo (2020)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Recognized by the Department of Physics and Astronomy for outstanding teaching (2019, &amp;lsquo;20)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Early Researcher Award, Ontario Government (2019)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Distinguished PhD Dissertation Award, University of Maryland (2012-13)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Teaching&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;PHYS 701 (Graduate Quantum Physics, Fall &amp;lsquo;22)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;PHYS 234 (Quantum Physics I, Winter 2019, &amp;lsquo;20, &amp;lsquo;21, &amp;lsquo;22, &amp;lsquo;24)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;PHYS 393 (Physical Optics, Winter 2020, &amp;lsquo;22, &amp;lsquo;24)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;PHYS 256 (Geometrical and Physical Optics, Fall 2017, &amp;lsquo;18, &amp;lsquo;22)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Outreach&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Islam is actively involved with several science outreach efforts.
His activities at IQC include developing demonstration experiments (such as a &amp;lsquo;dust ion trap&amp;rsquo;) and conducting lab visits especially for young students.
He is a co-founder of &lt;a href="https://bigyan.org.in" target="_blank"&gt;bigyan.org.in&lt;/a&gt;

, a leading online science outreach platform in the Bengali (বাংলা) language. Bigyan (বিজ্ঞান, means science in Bengali) initiatives have been highlighted in Indian national media (such as &lt;a href="https://www.ndtv.com/education/national-science-day-origami-paper-microscopes-to-be-given-to-rural-schools-by-bengali-science-porta-1664177" target="_blank"&gt;NDTV&lt;/a&gt;

 and &lt;a href="https://indiabioscience.org/columns/indian-scenario/bigyan-org-in-a-science-outreach-platform-by-researchers-in-bengali" target="_blank"&gt;IndiaBioscience&lt;/a&gt;

).&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>21 Jan 2020 - Paper on Machine learning published</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20200121_machine_learning_paper_published/</link><pubDate>Tue, 21 Jan 2020 22:25:52 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20200121_machine_learning_paper_published/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;“Machine learning design of a trapped-ion quantum spin simulator” is published in &lt;a href="https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.1088/2058-9565/ab657a" target="_blank"&gt;Quantum Science and Technology 5 (2020) 024001&lt;/a&gt;, (&lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1910.02496" target="_blank"&gt; arXiv.1910.02496&lt;/a&gt;). We numerically demonstrate that a machine learning neural network can be used to efficiently solve a non-linear inversion problem in an analog trapped-ion quantum simulator. The method generates experimental control parameters (such as laser intensities on each ions) needed to program a quantum simulator, in particular, to engineer an arbitrary spin lattice geometry in one, two, and three dimensions using a linear chain of ions!&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Machine learning design of a trapped-ion quantum spin simulator</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2020-machine-learning-design-of-a-trapped-ion-quantum-spin-simulator/</link><pubDate>Tue, 21 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2020-machine-learning-design-of-a-trapped-ion-quantum-spin-simulator/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Trapped ion quantum simulators can in principle simulate an arbitrarily connected spin model. This requires precise programming of the ions with laser beams. In this paper, we numerically show that modern machine learning methods can be employed to program a trapped ion quantum simulator to simulate spin Hamiltonians on an arbitrary lattice geometry. This work is a collaboration with Prof. Roger Melko&amp;rsquo;s group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt; Trapped ions have emerged as one of the highest quality platforms for the
quantum simulation of interacting spin models of interest to various fields of
physics. In such simulators, two effective spins can be made to interact with
arbitrary strengths by coupling to the collective vibrational or phonon states
of ions, controlled by precisely tuned laser beams. However, the task of
determining laser control parameters required for a given spin-spin interaction
graph is a type of inverse problem, which can be highly mathematically complex.
In this paper, we adapt a modern machine learning technique developed for
similar inverse problems to the task of finding the laser control parameters
for a number of interaction graphs. We demonstrate that typical graphs, forming
regular lattices of interest to physicists, can easily be produced for up to 50
ions using a single GPU workstation. The scaling of the machine learning method
suggests that this can be expanded to hundreds of ions with moderate additional
computational effort.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Michael Spinazze</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/michael-spinazze/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 21:42:32 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/michael-spinazze/</guid><description/></item><item><title>17 Dec 2019 - A review on trapped-ion quantum simulation!</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20191217_qsim_review_arxiv/</link><pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2019 22:25:49 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20191217_qsim_review_arxiv/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Here is a pre-print version of a review article on quantum simulation with trapped ions. The article focuses on analog spin simulation, and discusses the progress in this field so far. (&lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1912.07845" target="_blank"&gt;arxiv.1912.07845&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Sarah Mayer</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/sarah-mayer/</link><pubDate>Sat, 07 Dec 2019 22:01:38 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/sarah-mayer/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Niel Mistry</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/niel-mistry/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 Dec 2019 22:01:37 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/niel-mistry/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Joshua Da Costa</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/joshua-da-costa/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 Dec 2019 22:01:36 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/joshua-da-costa/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Joshua was an undergraduate co-op student in the QITI group for Spring and Fall 2019. His contributions included building radio-frequency amplifier boxes for driving AOMs.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>8 Oct 2019 - Machine learning for a quantum simulator!</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20191008_machine_learning_arxiv/</link><pubDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2019 22:25:42 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20191008_machine_learning_arxiv/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Our manuscript “Machine learning design of a trapped-ion quantum spin simulator” is on &lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1910.02496" target="_blank"&gt; arXiv.1910.02496&lt;/a&gt;. We demonstrate that a machine learning neural network can be used to efficiently engineer an arbitrary spin-spin interaction graph on an analog quantum simulator.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Holographic Optical Manipulation of Trapped Ions for Quantum Simulation</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2019-holographic-optical-manipulation-of-trapped-ions-for-quantum-simulation/</link><pubDate>Wed, 02 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2019-holographic-optical-manipulation-of-trapped-ions-for-quantum-simulation/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Trapped ion is one of the leading platforms for quantum simulation experiment due to its long coherence time and high fidelity state initialization, detection, and manipulation. To individually address ions at a single-ion level, it requires sophisticated optical engineering. In the thesis, we present a novel single qubit addressing system that is immune to imperfections of optical imaging and can scale to different size of the system. The technique is based on digital light processing with a commercially available digital micro-mirror device (DMD). A DMD is a 2D array that consists of tiny micro-mirrors that can be individually manipulated. It is commonly used in movie projectors to modulate the intensity of the light to create the desired image. However, using this technology to ions will require more sophisticated controls over optical wavefronts of the laser beams, for example, the necessity to manipulate the optical phase. It can be achieved by using the DMD as a programmable hologram, which can then be used to characterize and compensate for any imaging imperfections as well. We developed a new iterative Fourier transform algorithm (IFTA) for calculating the holograms. In the simulation, our algorithm shows more than one order of magnitude improvement in accuracy comparing to previously proposed algorithms. We experimentally demonstrated this holographic beam shaping technique with the optical aberration being compensated. The laser we used in the experiment is in the ultraviolet (UV) regime that is close to the optical transition used for manipulating $^{171}\mathrm{Yb}^+$ qubits. The short wavelength makes it more susceptible to environmental disturbance. Also, we proposed and experimentally demonstrated a new scheme that enables holographic controls over lights with multiple laser frequencies simultaneously by combing the DMD with an acousto-optical modulator (AOM). The AOM splits the light and illuminates different zones of the DMD. Each zone has its own hologram forming one frequency channel for addressing. This opens the possibility to engineer more complex Hamiltonian for quantum simulation. For example, we can engineer arbitrary spin-spin interaction graphs by applying the M\o lmer-S\o rensen scheme on this new setup.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Design and Construction of an Ion Trapping Apparatus for Quantum Simulation Experiments</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2019-design-and-construction-of-an-ion-trapping-apparatus-for-quantum-simulation-experiments/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2019-design-and-construction-of-an-ion-trapping-apparatus-for-quantum-simulation-experiments/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;The trapped ions platform represents an excellent framework for Quantum information science experiments. Long coherence times, extremely high state initialization and detection fidelity, inherent full-connectivity between qubits are some features that make trapped ions the ideal qubits. It is the same features that make this platform extremely suitable for quantum simulation of various physical phenomenon, particularly quantum spin models. In this thesis, I present the design and construction of an ion trapping apparatus for quantum simulation experiments. This apparatus is operational and is used for the trapping of ionized Yb atoms. The 6 electrodes of the trap, two of which are needle electrodes, are made out of tungsten. I discuss the unique technique we use to make tungsten needle electrodes. The design, construction, and testing of the Yb source, used to produce a thermal beam of Yb atoms, is also discussed.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>24 Sept 2019 - Early Researcher Award for Rajibul!</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20190924_era/</link><pubDate>Tue, 24 Sep 2019 22:25:38 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20190924_era/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Rajibul is recognized with the Ontario ‘Early Researcher Award’! &lt;a href="https://uwaterloo.ca/institute-for-quantum-computing/news/rajibul-islam-recognized-early-researcher-award" target="_blank"&gt;Read the IQC news coverage.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>11-13 Sept 2019 - Nikhil and Gilbert graduate with MSc!</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20190911_gilbert_nikhil_msc_graduation/</link><pubDate>Wed, 11 Sep 2019 22:25:33 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20190911_gilbert_nikhil_msc_graduation/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Congratulations to Gilbert and Nikhil for successfully defending their master’s thesis! They will continue their journey with the QITI group as PhD students.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Nikolay Videnov</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/nikolay-videnov/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/nikolay-videnov/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Nikolay did his MSc thesis on designing an open-source quantum computer (QuantumION) in Prof. Islam&amp;rsquo;s group, and worked as undergraduate co-op students in the same group.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>13 Aug 2019 - Yb+ ions</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20190813_ion-pics/</link><pubDate>Tue, 13 Aug 2019 22:25:26 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20190813_ion-pics/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Here’s a picture of eight laser-cooled Ytterbium (174 isotope) ions in a linear chain! The image was taken using an off-the-shelf Thorlabs 0.1 NA objective and a cheap (~$300) CMOS camera. The ions are approximately 8 microns apart. &lt;a href="https://uwaterloo.ca/physics-astronomy/news/first-look-laser-cooled-ions" target="_blank"&gt;Read more on the Physics and Astronomy webpage.&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>6 Jun 2019 - invited talk at CAP congress!</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20190806_cap_invited_talk/</link><pubDate>Tue, 06 Aug 2019 22:25:15 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20190806_cap_invited_talk/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Rajibul gives an invited talk at the Canadian Association of Physicists (CAP) congress at Simon Fraser University.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Duale Omar</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/duale-omar/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Aug 2019 22:01:35 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/duale-omar/</guid><description/></item><item><title>19 July 2019 - first ions!</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20190719_first_ions/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Jul 2019 22:25:26 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20190719_first_ions/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;We have have trapped, laser-cooled, and crystallized Ytterbium ions in a four-rod Paul trap!&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>27 Jun 2019 - new home of the QITI lab!</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20190627_new_home_qiti/</link><pubDate>Thu, 27 Jun 2019 22:25:22 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20190627_new_home_qiti/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;We have moved into our new lab-space in the basement of QNC building (QNC B221).&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>12 Jun 2019 - Sainath awarded!</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20190612_sainath_dean_of_science_award/</link><pubDate>Wed, 12 Jun 2019 22:25:19 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20190612_sainath_dean_of_science_award/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Sainath receives the Dean of Science Award for his MSc thesis! Congratulations!&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>27 May 2019 - talks and posters at DAMOP 2019</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20190527_damop2019/</link><pubDate>Mon, 27 May 2019 22:25:12 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20190527_damop2019/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Sainath, Gilbert, and Rajibul are attending the DAMOP meeting of the American Physical Society at Milwuakee, WI. Sainath will present a contributed talk and Gilbert will present a poster. Matt Day from Crystal Senko’s group will also present a poster highlighting ‘QuantumIon’ a joint research project between Rajibul’s and Crystal’s group to build an open-access trapped ion quantum computer for researchers.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>6 May 2019 - New co-ops!</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20190506_new_co-op_duale_josh/</link><pubDate>Mon, 06 May 2019 22:25:09 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20190506_new_co-op_duale_josh/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Duale Omar and Josh Da Costa join the group as undergraduate co-op students for the Spring term. Welcome to the team!&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>2 May 2019 - Rajibul in the land of Breaking Bad!</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20190502_unm_seminar/</link><pubDate>Thu, 02 May 2019 22:25:06 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20190502_unm_seminar/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Rajibul gives a seminar and interacts with researchers at the Center for Quantum Information and Control (CQuIC), University of New Mexico.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>26 Apr 2019 - paper on npj Quantum Information</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20190426_paper_npjqi/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 Apr 2019 22:25:03 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20190426_paper_npjqi/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;“Dynamical Hamiltonian engineering of 2D rectangular lattices in a one-dimensional ion chain” is published in npj Quantum Information (Nature Publishing Group). (&lt;a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41534-019-0147-x" target="_blank"&gt;npj Quantum Information 5, 32 (2019)&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Dynamical Hamiltonian engineering of 2D rectangular lattices in a one-dimensional ion chain</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2019-dynamic-hamiltonian-engineering-of-2d-rectangular-lattices-in-a-one-dimensional-ion-chain/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2019-dynamic-hamiltonian-engineering-of-2d-rectangular-lattices-in-a-one-dimensional-ion-chain/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;In this publication, we theoretically and numerically demonstrate a powerful analog-digital hybrid quantum simulation protocol that can be used to simulate spin-dynamics on a two dimensional lattice using a linear chain of ions. The simulation protocol makes use of native long range interactions between trapped ion spins, that are then digitally modified to achieve the target spin-spin interaction graph. On one hand, the hybrid simulation scheme is more flexible and requires less experimental control over individual ions than an analog quantum simulation, where the Hamiltonian is simulated by fine-tuning the control parameters. On the other hand, the hybrid simulation scheme does not build the entire time evolution out of quantum logic gates, unlike a fully digital quantum simulator, and therefore is more robust against Trotterization errors. This work is performed in collaboration with researchers from University of California, Berkeley and Army Research Laboratory, Maryland.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>16 Apr 2019 - Gilbert and Yi Hong present talks at TUCAN</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20190416_tucan/</link><pubDate>Tue, 16 Apr 2019 22:25:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20190416_tucan/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Two talks from the QITI group by Chung-You (Gilbert) Shih and Yi Hong Teoh were presented at the second Toronto Ultra-cold Atom Network (&lt;a href="https://uwaterloo.ca/institute-for-quantum-computing/events/toronto-ultracold-atom-network-tucan-meeting-2019" target="_blank"&gt;TUCAN&lt;/a&gt;) meeting hosted by University of Waterloo. Gilbert talked about efficient algorithms to generate amplitude holograms for optical manipulation, and Yi Hong discussed machine learning methods to program a quantum simulator.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Natasha Willis</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/natasha-willis/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Apr 2019 22:01:34 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/natasha-willis/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Natasha Willis
Email:
()&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Daniel Francis Julien Neitzert</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/daniel-francis-julien-neitzert/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Apr 2019 22:01:32 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/daniel-francis-julien-neitzert/</guid><description/></item><item><title>7 Jan 2019 - Welcome to new co-ops!</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20190107_new_co-ops_daniel_nathasha/</link><pubDate>Mon, 07 Jan 2019 22:24:57 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20190107_new_co-ops_daniel_nathasha/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Natasha Willis and Daniel Julien-Nietzert join the group for the Winter term as undergraduate co-op students. Welcome to the team!&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Luyao Wang</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/luyao-wang/</link><pubDate>Fri, 07 Dec 2018 22:01:31 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/luyao-wang/</guid><description/></item><item><title>1 Sep 2018 - Welcome to Manas!</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20180901_manas_joins/</link><pubDate>Sat, 01 Sep 2018 22:24:50 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20180901_manas_joins/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Dr. Manas Sajjan joins the group for a graduate school in experimental quantum physics, after successfully completing his first PhD at University of Chicago in theoretical chemistry!&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>22 Aug 2018 - Rajibul at KITP, Santa Barbara</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20180822_kitp_talk/</link><pubDate>Wed, 22 Aug 2018 22:24:47 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20180822_kitp_talk/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Rajibul gives the &amp;rsquo;experimentalist of the week&amp;rsquo; talk at the Dynamics of Quantum Information program at KITP, UC Santa Barbara. [&lt;a href="http://online.kitp.ucsb.edu/online/dynq18/islam/" target="_blank"&gt;Video&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>18 Aug 2018 - proposal for a hybrid quantum simulation</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20180818_hybrid_simulation_arxiv/</link><pubDate>Sat, 18 Aug 2018 22:24:35 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20180818_hybrid_simulation_arxiv/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Our experimentally feasible theoretical proposal to create 2D spin lattices from a one dimensional chain of ions is on arXiv! It is a collaboration with UC Berkeley and Army Research Laboratory. (&lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1808.06124" target="_blank"&gt;arXiv.1808.06124&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>15 Aug 2018 - Nik presents at CUPC!</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20180815_nik_cupc/</link><pubDate>Wed, 15 Aug 2018 22:24:31 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20180815_nik_cupc/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Undergraduate researcher Nikolay Videnov presents his work on making an injection locked diode laser at 369.5 nm at the Canadian Undergraduate Physics Conference (CUPC) at University of Alberta.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>7 Aug 2018 - Sainath defends MSc thesis!</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20180807_sainath_msc_defense/</link><pubDate>Tue, 07 Aug 2018 22:24:24 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20180807_sainath_msc_defense/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Sainath defends his &lt;a href="https://uwspace.uwaterloo.ca/handle/10012/13742" target="_blank"&gt;M.Sc thesis&lt;/a&gt; successfully! He will continue as a PhD student in the group. Congratulations, Sainath!&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Developing Theoretical and Experimental Tools for a Hybrid Quantum Simulator Based on Trapped Ions</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2018-developing-theoretical-and-experimental-tools-for-a-hybrid-quantum-simulator-based-on-trapped-ions/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2018-developing-theoretical-and-experimental-tools-for-a-hybrid-quantum-simulator-based-on-trapped-ions/</guid><description/></item><item><title>28 May 2018 - we are at DAMOP</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20180528_damop/</link><pubDate>Mon, 28 May 2018 22:24:20 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20180528_damop/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Gilbert, Sainath, Nikhil, and Rajibul attend the annual meeting of the Division of Atomic Molecular and Optical Physics (DAMOP) of the American Physical Society (APS) in Fort Lauderdale. We present two posters.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>1 May 2018 - Welcome to Roland and Yi Hong!</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20180501_roland_yi-hong_joins/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 May 2018 22:24:16 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20180501_roland_yi-hong_joins/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Dr. Roland Hablutzel joins the QITI team as a postdoc from the Centre for Quantum Technologies, Singapore. We also welcome undergraduate researcher Yi Hong Teoh!&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Kaleb Ruscitti</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/kaleb-ruscitti/</link><pubDate>Mon, 30 Apr 2018 22:01:30 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/kaleb-ruscitti/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Kaleb was an undergraduate co-op student in Fall, 2017. He worked on digital light processing devices.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Single-Atom Heat Machines Enabled by Energy Quantization</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2018-single-atom-heat-machines-enabled-by-energy-quantization/</link><pubDate>Wed, 25 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2018-single-atom-heat-machines-enabled-by-energy-quantization/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Quantization of energy is a quintessential characteristic of quantum systems.
Here we analyze its effects on the operation of Otto cycle heat machines and
show that energy quantization alone may alter and increase machine performance
in terms of output power, efficiency, and even operation mode. Our results
demonstrate that quantum thermodynamics enable the realization of classically
inconceivable Otto machines, such as those with an incompressible working
fluid. We propose to measure these effects experimentally using a laser-cooled
trapped ion as a microscopic heat machine.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>13 Apr 2018 - first TUCAN meeting at McMaster!</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20180413_tucan/</link><pubDate>Fri, 13 Apr 2018 22:24:12 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20180413_tucan/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Entire QITI team visits McMaster University to attend the first Toronto Ultracold Atoms Network (TUCAN) meeting. Fereshteh and Sainath give talks.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>15 Mar 2018 - Kaleb at PhUnC!</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20180315_kaleb_phunc/</link><pubDate>Thu, 15 Mar 2018 22:24:06 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20180315_kaleb_phunc/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Undergraduate researcher Kaleb Ruscitti presents our research on holographic beam shaping with UV light at the PhUnC conference at Western University.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>1 Jan 2018 - Welcome to Sainath!</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20180101_sainath_joins/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2018 22:23:58 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20180101_sainath_joins/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Sainath Motlakunta joins the group to work on his M.Sc thesis project. Kaleb Ruscitti and Nikolay Videnov come back to the group as undergraduate researchers! Kaleb will spend his Jan-Apr co-op term, and Nik will spend his Jan-Aug co-op term in the lab!&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Ilango Maran</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/ilango-maran/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Dec 2017 22:01:29 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/ilango-maran/</guid><description/></item><item><title>1 Sep 2017 - First graduate students!</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20170901_gilbert_nikhil_join/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Sep 2017 22:23:45 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20170901_gilbert_nikhil_join/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Chung-You (Gilbert) Shih from National Taiwan University and Nikhil Kotibhaskar from Indian Institute of Science join the IQC-QITI group as graduate students.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Louisa (Ruixue) Huang</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/louisa-huang/</link><pubDate>Mon, 07 Aug 2017 22:01:27 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/louisa-huang/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Jieren Deng</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/jieren-deng/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Aug 2017 22:01:28 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/jieren-deng/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Multislip Friction with a Single Ion</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2017-multislip-friction-with-a-single-ion/</link><pubDate>Mon, 24 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2017-multislip-friction-with-a-single-ion/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;A trapped ion transported along a periodic potential is studied as a
paradigmatic nanocontact frictional interface. The combination of the periodic
corrugation potential and a harmonic trapping potential creates a
one-dimensional energy landscape with multiple local minima, corresponding to
multistable stick-slip friction. We measure the probabilities of slipping to
the various minima for various corrugations and transport velocities. The
observed probabilities show that the multislip regime can be reached
dynamically at smaller corrugations than would be possible statically, and can
be described by an equilibrium Boltzmann model. While a clear microscopic
signature of multislip behavior is observed for the ion motion, the frictional
force and dissipation are only weakly affected by the transition to multistable
potentials.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>28 Jun 2017 - first (temporary) home of the QITI lab!</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20170628_temp_home_qiti_lab/</link><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jun 2017 22:23:38 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20170628_temp_home_qiti_lab/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;We move into a temporary laboratory space on the third floor of the Quantum Nano Center! Our basement lab will undergo a major renovation before we can move into the space.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Tony Kappen</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/tony-kappen/</link><pubDate>Sun, 07 May 2017 22:01:26 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/tony-kappen/</guid><description/></item><item><title>1 May 2017 - Fereshteh joins as a postdoc!</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20170501_fereshteh_joins/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 May 2017 22:23:30 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20170501_fereshteh_joins/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Dr. Fereshteh Rajabi joins the group as an IQC theory postdoc!&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>3 Jan 2017 - First students join QITI group!</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20170103_first_students/</link><pubDate>Tue, 03 Jan 2017 22:23:25 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/news/20170103_first_students/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Tony Kappen and Kaleb Ruscitti join as the first two undergraduate researchers of the group!&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Ultra-precise holographic beam shaping for microscopic quantum control</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2016-ultra-precise-holographic-beam-shaping-for-microscopic-quantum-control/</link><pubDate>Tue, 14 Jun 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2016-ultra-precise-holographic-beam-shaping-for-microscopic-quantum-control/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;High-resolution addressing of individual ultracold atoms, trapped ions or
solid state emitters allows for exquisite control in quantum optics
experiments. This becomes possible through large aperture magnifying optics
that project microscopic light patterns with diffraction limited performance.
We use programmable amplitude holograms generated on a digital micromirror
device to create arbitrary microscopic beam shapes with full phase and
amplitude control. The system self-corrects for aberrations of up to several
$\lambda$ and reduces them to $\lambda/50$, leading to light patterns with a
precision on the $10^{-4}$ level. We demonstrate aberration-compensated beam
shaping in an optical lattice experiment and perform single-site addressing in
a quantum gas microscope for $^{87}$Rb.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Measuring entanglement entropy in a quantum many-body system</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2015-measuring-entanglement-entropy-in-a-quantum-many-body-system/</link><pubDate>Wed, 02 Dec 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2015-measuring-entanglement-entropy-in-a-quantum-many-body-system/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Entanglement is one of the most intriguing features of quantum mechanics. It
describes non-local correlations between quantum objects, and is at the heart
of quantum information sciences. Entanglement is rapidly gaining prominence in
diverse fields ranging from condensed matter to quantum gravity. Despite this
generality, measuring entanglement remains challenging. This is especially true
in systems of interacting delocalized particles, for which a direct
experimental measurement of spatial entanglement has been elusive. Here, we
measure entanglement in such a system of itinerant particles using quantum
interference of many-body twins. Leveraging our single-site resolved control of
ultra-cold bosonic atoms in optical lattices, we prepare and interfere two
identical copies of a many-body state. This enables us to directly measure
quantum purity, Renyi entanglement entropy, and mutual information. These
experiments pave the way for using entanglement to characterize quantum phases
and dynamics of strongly-correlated many-body systems.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Strongly correlated quantum walks in optical lattices</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2015-strongly-correlated-quantum-walks-in-optical-lattices/</link><pubDate>Thu, 12 Mar 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2015-strongly-correlated-quantum-walks-in-optical-lattices/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Full control over the dynamics of interacting, indistinguishable quantum
particles is an important prerequisite for the experimental study of strongly
correlated quantum matter and the implementation of high-fidelity quantum
information processing. Here we demonstrate such control over the quantum walk&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the quantum mechanical analogue of the classical random walk - in the strong
interaction regime. Using interacting bosonic atoms in an optical lattice, we
directly observe fundamental effects such as the emergence of correlations in
two-particle quantum walks, as well as strongly correlated Bloch oscillations
in tilted optical lattices. Our approach can be scaled to larger systems,
greatly extending the class of problems accessible via quantum walks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description></item><item><title>Beat note stabilization of mode-locked lasers for quantum information processing</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2014-beat-note-stabilization-of-mode-locked-lasers-for-quantum-information-processing/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 Jun 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2014-beat-note-stabilization-of-mode-locked-lasers-for-quantum-information-processing/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;We stabilize a chosen radiofrequency beat note between two optical fields
derived from the same mode-locked laser pulse train, in order to coherently
manipulate quantum information. This scheme does not require access or active
stabilization of the laser repetition rate. We implement and characterize this
external lock, in the context of two-photon stimulated Raman transitions
between the hyperfine ground states of trapped 171-Yb+ quantum bits.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Quantum Catalysis of Magnetic Phase Transitions in a Quantum Simulator</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2013-quantum-catalysis-of-magnetic-phase-transitions-in-a-quantum-simulator/</link><pubDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2013-quantum-catalysis-of-magnetic-phase-transitions-in-a-quantum-simulator/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;We control quantum fluctuations to create the ground state magnetic phases of
a classical Ising model with a tunable longitudinal magnetic field using a
system of 6 to 10 atomic ion spins. Due to the long-range Ising interactions,
the various ground state spin configurations are separated by multiple
first-order phase transitions, which in our zero temperature system cannot be
driven by thermal fluctuations. We instead use a transverse magnetic field as a
quantum catalyst to observe the first steps of the complete fractal devil&amp;rsquo;s
staircase, which emerges in the thermodynamic limit and can be mapped to a
large number of many-body and energy-optimization problems.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Emergence and Frustration of Magnetism with Variable-Range Interactions in a Quantum Simulator</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2013-emergence-and-frustration-of-magnetic-order-with-variable-range-interactions-in-a-trapped-ion-quantum-simulator/</link><pubDate>Fri, 03 May 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2013-emergence-and-frustration-of-magnetic-order-with-variable-range-interactions-in-a-trapped-ion-quantum-simulator/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Frustration, or the competition between interacting components of a network,
is often responsible for the complexity of many body systems, from social and
neural networks to protein folding and magnetism. In quantum magnetic systems,
frustration arises naturally from competing spin-spin interactions given by the
geometry of the spin lattice or by the presence of long-range antiferromagnetic
couplings. Frustrated magnetism is a hallmark of poorly understood systems such
as quantum spin liquids, spin glasses and spin ices, whose ground states are
massively degenerate and can carry high degrees of quantum entanglement. The
controlled study of frustrated magnetism in materials is hampered by short
dynamical time scales and the presence of impurities, while numerical modeling
is generally intractable when dealing with dynamics beyond N~30 particles.
Alternatively, a quantum simulator can be exploited to directly engineer
prescribed frustrated interactions between controlled quantum systems, and
several small-scale experiments have moved in this direction. In this article,
we perform a quantum simulation of a long-range antiferromagnetic quantum Ising
model with a transverse field, on a crystal of up to N = 16 trapped Yb+ atoms.
We directly control the amount of frustration by continuously tuning the range
of interaction and directly measure spin correlation functions and their
dynamics through spatially-resolved spin detection. We find a pronounced
dependence of the magnetic order on the amount of frustration, and extract
signatures of quantum coherence in the resulting phases.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Quantum simulation of spin models on an arbitrary lattice with trapped ions</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2012-korenblit-quantum-simulation-of-spin-models-on-an-arbitrary-lattice-with-trapped-ions/</link><pubDate>Thu, 27 Sep 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2012-korenblit-quantum-simulation-of-spin-models-on-an-arbitrary-lattice-with-trapped-ions/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;A collection of trapped atomic ions represents one of the most attractive platforms for the quantum simulation of interacting spin networks and quantum magnetism. Spin-dependent optical dipole forces applied to an ion crystal create long-range effective spin–spin interactions and allow the simulation of spin Hamiltonians that possess nontrivial phases and dynamics. Here we show how the appropriate design of laser fields can provide for arbitrary multidimensional spin–spin interaction graphs even for the case of a linear spatial array of ions. This scheme uses currently available trap technology and is scalable to levels where the classical methods of simulation are intractable.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Quantum Simulation of Interacting Spin Models With Trapped Ions</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2012-quantum-simulation-of-interacting-spin-models-with-trapped-ions/</link><pubDate>Sat, 01 Sep 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2012-quantum-simulation-of-interacting-spin-models-with-trapped-ions/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Onset of a quantum phase transition with a trapped ion quantum simulator</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2011-onset-of-a-quantum-phase-transition-with-a-trapped-ion-quantum-simulator/</link><pubDate>Tue, 05 Jul 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2011-onset-of-a-quantum-phase-transition-with-a-trapped-ion-quantum-simulator/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;A quantum simulator is a well controlled quantum system that can simulate the
behavior of another quantum system which may require exponentially large
classical computing resources to understand otherwise. In the 1980s, Feynman
proposed the use of quantum logic gates on a standard controllable quantum
system to efficiently simulate the behavior of a model Hamiltonian. Recent
experiments using trapped ions and neutral atoms have realized quantum
simulation of Ising model in presence of external magnetic fields, and showed
almost arbitrary control in generating non-trivial Ising coupling patterns.
Here we use laser-cooled trapped 171-Yb+ ions to simulate the emergence of
magnetism in a system of interacting spins by implementing a fully-connected
non-uniform ferromagnetic Ising model in a transverse magnetic field. To link
this quantum simulation to condensed matter physics, we measure scalable
correlation functions and order parameters appropriate for the description of
larger systems, such as various moments of the magnetization. By increasing the
Ising coupling strengths compared with the external field, the crossover from
paramagnetism to ferromagnetic order sharpens as the system is scaled up from N
= 2 to 9 trapped ion spins. This points toward the onset of a quantum phase
transition that should become infinitely sharp as the system approaches the
macroscopic scale. We compare the measured ground state order to theory, which
may become intractable for non-uniform Ising couplings as the number of spins
grows beyond 20- 30 and even NP complete for a fully-connected frustrated Ising
model, making this experiment an important benchmark for large-scale quantum
simulation.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Quantum simulation and phase diagram of the transverse-field Ising model with three atomic spins</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2010-edwards-quantum-simulation-and-phase-diagram-of-the-transverse-field-ising-model-with-three-atomic-spins/</link><pubDate>Fri, 27 Aug 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2010-edwards-quantum-simulation-and-phase-diagram-of-the-transverse-field-ising-model-with-three-atomic-spins/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;We perform a quantum simulation of the Ising model with a transverse field using a collection of three trapped atomic ion spins. By adiabatically manipulating the Hamiltonian, we directly probe the ground state for a wide range of fields and form of the Ising couplings, leading to a phase diagram of magnetic order in this microscopic system. The technique is scalable to much larger numbers of trapped ion spins, where phase transitions approaching the thermodynamic limit can be studied in cases where theory becomes intractable.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Quantum simulation of frustrated Ising spins with trapped ions</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2010-quantum-simulation-of-frustrated-ising-spins-with-trapped-ions/</link><pubDate>Thu, 03 Jun 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2010-quantum-simulation-of-frustrated-ising-spins-with-trapped-ions/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Laser-cooled and trapped atomic ions form an ideal standard for the
simulation of interacting quantum spin models. Effective spins are represented
by appropriate internal energy levels within each ion, and the spins can be
measured with near-perfect efficiency using state-dependent fluorescence
techniques. By applying optical fields that exert optical dipole forces on the
ions, their Coulomb interaction can be modulated in ways that give rise to
long-range and tunable spin-spin interactions that can be reconfigured by
shaping the spectrum and pattern of the laser fields. Here we review the
theoretical mapping of atomic ions to interacting spin systems, the
experimental preparation of complex equilibrium states, and the study of
dynamical processes of this many-body interacting quantum system. The use of
such quantum simulators for studying spin models may inform our understanding
of exotic quantum materials and shed light on interacting quantum systems that
cannot be modeled with conventional computers.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Entanglement and Tunable Spin-Spin Couplings between Trapped Ions Using Multiple Transverse Modes</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2009-entanglement-and-tunable-spin-spin-couplings-between-trapped-ions-using-multiple-transverse-modes/</link><pubDate>Wed, 16 Sep 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2009-entanglement-and-tunable-spin-spin-couplings-between-trapped-ions-using-multiple-transverse-modes/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;We demonstrate tunable spin-spin couplings between trapped atomic ions,
mediated by laser forces on multiple transverse collective modes of motion. A
$\sigma_x \sigma_x$-type Ising interaction is realized between quantum bits
stored in the ground hyperfine clock states of Yb ions. We demonstrate
entangling gates and tailor the spin-spin couplings with two and three trapped
ions. The use of closely-spaced transverse modes provides a new class of
interactions relevant to quantum computing and simulation with large
collections of ions in a single crystal.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Large-scale quantum computation in an anharmonic linear ion trap</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2009-large-scale-quantum-computation-in-an-anharmonic-linear-ion-trap/</link><pubDate>Sat, 27 Jun 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2009-large-scale-quantum-computation-in-an-anharmonic-linear-ion-trap/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;We propose a large-scale quantum computer architecture by stabilizing a
single large linear ion chain in a very simple trap geometry. By confining ions
in an anharmonic linear trap with nearly uniform spacing between ions, we show
that high-fidelity quantum gates can be realized in large linear ion crystals
under the Doppler temperature based on coupling to a near-continuum of
transverse motional modes with simple shaped laser pulses.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>