<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Thesis on QUANTUM INFORMATION WITH TRAPPED IONS</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/tags/thesis/</link><description>Recent content in Thesis on QUANTUM INFORMATION WITH TRAPPED IONS</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 07 Aug 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/tags/thesis/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Autoregressive Generative Models for Many-body Physics</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2025-yihong-teoh-phd-thesis/</link><pubDate>Thu, 07 Aug 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2025-yihong-teoh-phd-thesis/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Many body physics, the study of emergent behavior from the microscopic interactions between countless degrees of freedom, is fundamental to our understanding of the universe. Understanding these systems enable the design and development of everything from materials, pharmaceuticals and even machine learning algorithms. However, to our knowledge, classical simulation of these systems are naturally insufficient and or inefficient.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recent developments in quantum processors herald a new age in the study of many body systems. The ability to process, extract and generalize the information from such devices is pertinent to new discoveries in the field.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Towards Large Scale Quantum Simulations with Trapped Ions: Programmable XY model, Precise Light Sensing, and Extreme High Vacuum</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2024-nikhil-kotibhaskar-phd-thesis/</link><pubDate>Wed, 04 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2024-nikhil-kotibhaskar-phd-thesis/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;We are currently witnessing a revolution in quantum technologies. Today&amp;rsquo;s controllable quantum devices have reached a complexity that makes it practically intractable to fully simulate their dynamics using current classical supercomputers.
Decades of fundamental research and development have led us to this point. In the coming years, billions of dollars in investments from governments and private entities are expected worldwide. Although general-purpose fault-tolerant quantum computers are expected to impact computing profoundly, today&amp;rsquo;s quantum devices are best suited for their analog quantum operation, where a well-controlled quantum simulator mimics the dynamics of the other quantum system being studied. This affords an advantage over classical simulators at the cost of a restricted set of physical phenomena that can be studied. Today&amp;rsquo;s quantum devices are already providing insights into large-scale entanglement, the underlying physics of high-temperature superconductivity, disordered quantum systems, and much more. Enhancing the capabilities of today&amp;rsquo;s analog quantum simulators requires adding more classes of interactions, reducing errors due to calibration and noise, and increasing the system size to allow larger-scale simulations.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Optimization of the Optical Infrastructure and Trapping Potential for a Quantum Processor Based on Trapped Barium Ions</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2024-xinghe-tan-msc-thesis/</link><pubDate>Fri, 02 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2024-xinghe-tan-msc-thesis/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Trapped ion quantum computers represent a cutting-edge quantum computing platform, keeping the highest reported state preparation and measurement fidelity of 99.97%. Recently, barium ion has emerged as the research interest of several teams due to its exceptional characteristics, including visible and inferred state transition frequencies, long-lived metastable states, and a simple hyperfine structure. Our research group aims to demonstrate trapping 16 133Ba+ ions on a micro-fabricated surface trap and build a quantum computing platform. In the long run, we intend to open access to this platform for the academic community to use. This project is named the QuantumIon project. The project started in 2019, just before the global pandemic. During the pandemic, the QuantumION team did not have the lab space and the components to prototype and benchmark subsystems in parallel with system design. Instead, the team designed the entire system on computers during the pandemic. I joined the QuantumION team in 2022 and performed the system assembly, validation and optimization when the pandemic restrictions were lifted. In this thesis, I describe the optimization of the optical system for delivering laser beams to the ions and the validation of a 0.6 NA imaging system that will be used to observe the ion fluorescence as a means of measuring its quantum state. While benchmarking the optical systems, I found that the performance of the components deviated from their ideal specifications, such as insertion loss. Therefore, I had to modify the system design to ensure the optical systems functioned in practice. In addition, I conducted a feasibility study on delivering an ablation laser via multimode fiber and simulated a trapping potential on the surface trap that achieved approximately even spacing for 12 out of the 16 trapped ions.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Towards Pulsed Telecom Laser Ablation Loading for an Ytterbium Ion Trap</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2023-monica-zhu-msc-thesis/</link><pubDate>Mon, 23 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2023-monica-zhu-msc-thesis/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Trapped ion system is a promising platform for quantum computing, with long qubit coherence, high gate and measurement fidelities. To harness the full potential of the trapped ion system, it is imperative to employ an efficient ion loading scheme. While the conventional oven loading method has its drawbacks, such as slow loading time, resource wastage, and potential contamination that can compromise system longevity and introduce decoherence, the pulsed laser ablation loading offers a promising alternative. This method enables fast, resource efficient, and controllable generation of a neutral atomic flux. This thesis explores the development of a 1.57 μm pulsed laser ablation (PLA) loading scheme for an Ytterbium ion trap. With endeavors in theoretical simulations and experimental setups designed with a keen emphasis on laser-induced damage thresholds, we successfully generated a neutral flux from the ablation laser, acquired a comprehensive isotope spectrum, and estimated the velocity distribution in the atomic plume. A fiber-coupled ablation delivery module was also designed and proved feasible along with the main ablation experiments. This study establishes a solid groundwork for the future integration of pulsed laser ablation loading into our trap system and provides invaluable empirical insights into the use of high-power infrared (IR) pulsed lasers.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Programmable Individual Addressing and Floquet Hamiltonian Dynamics in a Trapped Ion Quantum Processor</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2023-chung-you-shih-phd-thesis/</link><pubDate>Tue, 26 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2023-chung-you-shih-phd-thesis/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Trapped ions have been gaining traction as a platform for quantum information processing (QIP) in both academia and industry over the last decade. Their long coherence time, high fidelity gate operations, and built-in all-to-all connectivity are some of the key features that make trapped ions promising. However, to unlock the full potential of the trapped ion platform, sophisticated quantum controls are required. In this thesis, we present our efforts in individual optical addressing to control an ion&amp;rsquo;s quantum state at an individual level, as well as efforts in generating complex and time-dependent Hamiltonians through arbitrary radio frequency (RF) waveform generation.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Developing a Large-Scale, Programmable Trapped Ion Quantum Simulator with In Situ Mid-Circuit Measurement and Reset</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2023-sainath-motlakunta-phd-thesis/</link><pubDate>Mon, 25 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2023-sainath-motlakunta-phd-thesis/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Quantum simulators are a valuable resource for studying complex many-body systems. With their ability to provide near-term advantages, analog quantum simulators show great promise. In this thesis, my aim is to describe the construction of a large-scale trapped-ion based analog quantum simulator with several objectives in mind: controllability, minimal external decoherence, an expandable toolkit for quantum simulations, enhanced stability through robust design practices, and pushing the boundaries of error correction. One of the techniques that significantly expands the range of simulations possible in trapped ions is site-selective mid-circuit measurements and resets. This technique enables the exploration of new classes of quantum simulations, including measurement-based phase transitions and reservoir engineering with controlled dissipation. Additionally, mid-circuit measurements play a crucial role and serve as one of the key factors in achieving error-correction in trapped ions. In this thesis, I address the challenges associated with implementing mid-circuit measurements and discuss strategies for achieving state-of-the-art fidelities in these processes within our simulator. In this thesis, I present the results demonstrating the high-fidelity preservation of an &amp;ldquo;asset&amp;rdquo; ion qubit while simultaneously resetting or measuring a neighboring &amp;ldquo;process&amp;rdquo; qubit located a few microns away. The results show that we achieve a probability of accidental measurement of the asset qubit below 1×10⁻³ while resetting the process qubit. Similarly, when applying a detection beam on the same neighboring qubit to achieve fast detection times, the probability remains below 4×10⁻³ at a distance of 6 μm, which is four times the addressing Gaussian beam waist. These low probabilities correspond to the preservation of the quantum state of the asset qubit with fidelities above 99.9% for state reset and 99.6% for state measurement. One of the many fascinating aspects of physics that can be explored through the use of site-selective mid-circuit resets is reservoir engineering. In this thesis, I discuss a protocol utilizing reservoir engineering to efficiently cool the spin state of a subsystem that is coupled to a reservoir with controlled dissipation. I demonstrate the effectiveness of this protocol through numerical simulations performed to optimize it for our experimental parameters. By leveraging the site-selective mid-circuit resets mentioned earlier, I successfully conduct a proof-of-principle dissipative many-body cooling experiment based on reservoir engineering. Through analog quantum simulation, I am able to demonstrate the lowering of energy within the system. In addition to the above explorations, another important aspect of this thesis is the description of the design, fabrication, and assembly of a large-scale trapped ion quantum simulator called the Blade trap. I discuss the essential features of this system that include accommodating a significant number of ions, extending ion lifetimes and coherence times, enabling precise control of ion spins and interactions, implementing efficient detection methods, and incorporating mid-circuit measurement capabilities. I also provide a detailed account of our approach to optimizing the design and fabrication of the blade-trap system, covering the trap itself, mechanical components, system internals, optics, and the critical ultra-high vacuum (UHV) assembly. Furthermore, comprehensive testing procedures are presented to evaluate the performance and stability of the Blade trap. I also describe the details about one of the significant challenges we faced in achieving and maintaining ultra-low pressure levels in the UHV system to ensure uninterrupted quantum simulation experiments with around 50 ions. High pressures can lead to detrimental collisions between ions and background atoms, necessitating re-trapping and introducing substantial overhead. Therefore, we aimed to achieve pressures in the range of 5×10⁻¹³ to 1×10⁻¹² mbar at room temperature, demanding meticulous optimization at the component level. Our journey to attain these pressures took approximately 2 to 3 years, complicated further by COVID-19 restrictions and equipment malfunctions. Despite the exhausting efforts, we successfully reached base pressures of less than 9×10⁻¹³ mbar in the vacuum chamber with partial internals. It is important to note that this measurement represents an upper limit due to gauge limitations.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>On the evaluation of quantum instruments with a consideration to measurements in trapped ion systems</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2022-darian-mclaren-msc-thesis/</link><pubDate>Thu, 08 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2022-darian-mclaren-msc-thesis/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Trapped ion chains have shown promise in their application as quantum simulators.
However, the close proximity of ions in the trap leads to operations such as state detection
causing loss of coherence of other ions due to imperfect beam addressing and absorption
of scattered photons during neighbouring ion fluorescence. In the first part of my thesis I
consider a Ytterbium 171 ion trap and calculate the probability of neighbouring ion photon
absorption. I additionally show how to use the Lindblad master equation to simulate the
dynamics of an ion under an attenuated beam, and provide a review of determining the
detection fidelity through histograms of photon detection counts.
I then return to the more abstract setting of non-destructive quantum measurements,
which are instrumental for fault-tolerant quantum computers. These non-destructive quantum measurements have both a quantum and classical output and hence must be described
through a quantum instrument as opposed to the typical representation of measurements
through POVM’s. It therefore becomes necessary to develop methods for evaluating quantum instruments. In this thesis I show that the process fidelity and diamond distance as
figures of merits on unitary channels may be generalized to figures of merits on quantum
instruments. I show that these figures of merit adequately capture the errors associated to
non-destructive measurements, and they additionally provide upper and lower bounds for
each other. Several examples are also given of computing the figures of merit on quantum
instruments under various noise models.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Coherent interactions and thermometry in a trapped ion quantum simulator</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2022-anthony-vogliano-msc-thesis/</link><pubDate>Fri, 02 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2022-anthony-vogliano-msc-thesis/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Quantum simulators are useful tools to study exotic systems which may be otherwise
intractable for a traditional computer. In particular, the trapped-ion platform has been a
leading candidate for use in quantum simulation experiments because of its high fidelity
state-preparation and measurement operations and its all-to-all connectivity. The relative
difficulty of interacting with the long lived hyperfine states of 171Yb+
ions make them
excellent choices for encoding information as the isolation creates stability against a noisy
environment. Maintaining coherence for such a long time opens the door for complex
coherent interactions, which are a backbone of quantum simulation experiments. One of
the most critical coherent operations for a trapped-ion quantum simulator is the entangling
Molmer-Sørenson interaction.
Building up to the Molmer-Sørenson interaction requires fine control over not just the
state of the quantum register, but also the motional state of the ion. For this reason,
cooling to near the ground state of motion is crucial to obtaining high fidelity experiments.
Characterizing the temperature in such systems can prove challenging, requiring coherent
techniques.
In this thesis, I describe my work towards preparing a Molmer-Sørenson interaction
for a 171Yb+
trapped ion quantum simulator. I detail the methods used to bring-up the
coherent Raman interactions, and characterize the Doppler cooling and Continuous Sideband Cooling (CSBC) techniques we use, their implementations on our system, and their
limitations. I characterize the temperature of our ions before and after CSBC using coherent methods, showing a 46x improvement in the motional state population and confirming
that post-CSBC the ions are in the Lamb-Dicke regime. I also summarize my efforts in
constructing a future ”blade trap” system with enough precision in the alignment of the
electrodes to eventually enable efficient cooling. I show preliminary evidence that 5um
precision in blade position should be feasible.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Robust Optical Engineering for a Trapped Ion Quantum Computer</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2022-ali-binai-motlagh-msc-thesis/</link><pubDate>Fri, 02 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2022-ali-binai-motlagh-msc-thesis/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Trapped ions are one of the leading platforms for the implementation of quantum information processing (QIP),
exhibiting one of the highest reported quantum gate and measurement fidelities. The challenge for the platform
now is to maintain these high quality operations while expanding the system size beyond the ∼10-30 qubits that
are available in today’s devices. Currently we are near completion of the construction of our trapped ion quantum
computer that will incorporate multiple isotopes of barium as qubits/qudits. Barium has several favourable properties
that make it the ideal ion for QIP and the aim of our device in the near future is to develop this species into
the premiere ion for QIP. The device in the future is hoped to serve as a cloud based resource for the Waterloo
research community, fostering collaborations between algorithms, error correction and atomic physics researchers,
that is ultimately hoped to expedite the development of trapped ion QIP. This thesis discusses the robust optical
engineering that went into the construction of this trapped ion quantum computer. We describe the details of the
continuous wave optical subsystems used for ion initialization, cooling, and measurements of the quantum states,
including the imaging system used to collect ion fluorescence. In addition, this thesis discusses the unique individual
addressing system that we have designed and built for performing single and two-qubit gates based on Raman transitions.
With this system we attain a relative intensity crosstalk between neighbouring ions on the order of 1e−4.
This is comparable to the best currently available implementations but our system provides additional optical
frequency and phase control knobs that allow for more control over quantum simulation and computation experiments.
Finally we will discuss the trap, its associated electronics and the vacuum system that houses our ions and atomic source.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Optical Design for an Open Access Trapped Ion Quantum Processor</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2021-videnov-msc-thesis/</link><pubDate>Tue, 31 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2021-videnov-msc-thesis/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;The future of quantum information is scaling to a ever larger number of qubits. Doing so will require advances in the approach for all aspects of current experimental systems. The QuantumION project is a large step in this direction. This project will provide an open-access trapped ion quantum processor for the research community. The necessary innovations for how QuantumION will be controlled and assembled represents a paradigm shift from ad-hock disparate systems running the experiment to a well engineered, integrated, quantum platform. These innovations will require coordinated work from many contributors, and this thesis covers a few specific aspects of QuantumION to which the author has contributed.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Experimental and theoretical investigations of radio-frequency and optical trapping potentials for atomic ions</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2020-sajjan-msc-thesis/</link><pubDate>Thu, 08 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2020-sajjan-msc-thesis/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Over the years, trapped ion have emerged as one of the premier candidates for universal quantum simulation due to its long coherence time, low initialization and detection errors, robust high-fidelity gate sets and fully connected yet tunable spin-graph. In this thesis we exclusively focus on the generation of the trapping potential in a four-rod trap, one of the most commonly studied ion-trapping architecture. We elaborate the fabrication of the trapping electrodes using electro-etching techniques and explore the underlying mechanism in details. We discuss how these electrodes are powered by DC and RF field to generate the confining potential responsible for trapping the ions of interest in 3D. We conclude by studying how this trapping potential can be modified by external means like using an optical tweezer. Employing such an optical tweezer we propose a new quantum-thermodynamic protocol which shall allow us to experimentally access the thermal properties of a mixed specie ion chain using a single-specie ion chain. The scheme is based on Jarzynski&amp;rsquo;s equality and obviates the need to trap dual-ionic species as far as illustrating the mechanical properties of the chain are concerned. We present results ratifying the utility of the proposal. The scheme is useful to obtain mode-specific thermal properties hitherto unexplored experimentally.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Holographic Optical Manipulation of Trapped Ions for Quantum Simulation</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2019-holographic-optical-manipulation-of-trapped-ions-for-quantum-simulation/</link><pubDate>Wed, 02 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2019-holographic-optical-manipulation-of-trapped-ions-for-quantum-simulation/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Trapped ion is one of the leading platforms for quantum simulation experiment due to its long coherence time and high fidelity state initialization, detection, and manipulation. To individually address ions at a single-ion level, it requires sophisticated optical engineering. In the thesis, we present a novel single qubit addressing system that is immune to imperfections of optical imaging and can scale to different size of the system. The technique is based on digital light processing with a commercially available digital micro-mirror device (DMD). A DMD is a 2D array that consists of tiny micro-mirrors that can be individually manipulated. It is commonly used in movie projectors to modulate the intensity of the light to create the desired image. However, using this technology to ions will require more sophisticated controls over optical wavefronts of the laser beams, for example, the necessity to manipulate the optical phase. It can be achieved by using the DMD as a programmable hologram, which can then be used to characterize and compensate for any imaging imperfections as well. We developed a new iterative Fourier transform algorithm (IFTA) for calculating the holograms. In the simulation, our algorithm shows more than one order of magnitude improvement in accuracy comparing to previously proposed algorithms. We experimentally demonstrated this holographic beam shaping technique with the optical aberration being compensated. The laser we used in the experiment is in the ultraviolet (UV) regime that is close to the optical transition used for manipulating $^{171}\mathrm{Yb}^+$ qubits. The short wavelength makes it more susceptible to environmental disturbance. Also, we proposed and experimentally demonstrated a new scheme that enables holographic controls over lights with multiple laser frequencies simultaneously by combing the DMD with an acousto-optical modulator (AOM). The AOM splits the light and illuminates different zones of the DMD. Each zone has its own hologram forming one frequency channel for addressing. This opens the possibility to engineer more complex Hamiltonian for quantum simulation. For example, we can engineer arbitrary spin-spin interaction graphs by applying the M\o lmer-S\o rensen scheme on this new setup.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Design and Construction of an Ion Trapping Apparatus for Quantum Simulation Experiments</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2019-design-and-construction-of-an-ion-trapping-apparatus-for-quantum-simulation-experiments/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2019-design-and-construction-of-an-ion-trapping-apparatus-for-quantum-simulation-experiments/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;The trapped ions platform represents an excellent framework for Quantum information science experiments. Long coherence times, extremely high state initialization and detection fidelity, inherent full-connectivity between qubits are some features that make trapped ions the ideal qubits. It is the same features that make this platform extremely suitable for quantum simulation of various physical phenomenon, particularly quantum spin models. In this thesis, I present the design and construction of an ion trapping apparatus for quantum simulation experiments. This apparatus is operational and is used for the trapping of ionized Yb atoms. The 6 electrodes of the trap, two of which are needle electrodes, are made out of tungsten. I discuss the unique technique we use to make tungsten needle electrodes. The design, construction, and testing of the Yb source, used to produce a thermal beam of Yb atoms, is also discussed.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Developing Theoretical and Experimental Tools for a Hybrid Quantum Simulator Based on Trapped Ions</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2018-developing-theoretical-and-experimental-tools-for-a-hybrid-quantum-simulator-based-on-trapped-ions/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2018-developing-theoretical-and-experimental-tools-for-a-hybrid-quantum-simulator-based-on-trapped-ions/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Quantum Simulation of Interacting Spin Models With Trapped Ions</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2012-quantum-simulation-of-interacting-spin-models-with-trapped-ions/</link><pubDate>Sat, 01 Sep 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2012-quantum-simulation-of-interacting-spin-models-with-trapped-ions/</guid><description/></item></channel></rss>