<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>QITI on QUANTUM INFORMATION WITH TRAPPED IONS</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/tags/qiti/</link><description>Recent content in QITI on QUANTUM INFORMATION WITH TRAPPED IONS</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/tags/qiti/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Optical field characterization at the fundamental limit of spatial resolution with a trapped ion</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2025_kotibhaskar_optical_field_characterization/</link><pubDate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2025_kotibhaskar_optical_field_characterization/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt; Optical systems capable of generating fields with sub-wavelength spatial features have become standard in science and engineering research and industry. Pertinent examples include atom- and ion-based quantum computers and optical lithography setups. So far, no tools exist to characterize such fields - both intensity and polarization - at sub-wavelength length scales. We use a single trapped atomic ion, confined to approximately 40 nm X 40 nm X 180 nm to sense a laser light field at a wavelength of 370 nm. With its spatial extent smaller than the absorption cross-section of a resonant detector, the ion-sensor operates at the fundamental limit of spatial resolution. Our technique relies on developing an analytical model of the ion-light interaction and using the model to extract the intensity and polarization. An important insight provided in this work is also that the inverse of this model can be learned, in a restricted sense, on a deep neural network, speeding up the intensity and polarization readout by five orders of magnitude. This speed-up makes the technique field-deployable to characterize optical instruments by probing light at the sub-wavelength scale.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>pySLM2: A full-stack python package for holographic beam shaping</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2024-shih-a-full-stack-python-package-for-holographic-beam-shaping/</link><pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2024-shih-a-full-stack-python-package-for-holographic-beam-shaping/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt; Holographic beam shaping using spatial light modulators (SLMs) as a reprogrammable hologram
offers a powerful tool for precise and flexible optical controls. It has been adopted for a wide
range of researches, including atom trapping, optical addressing
of individual quantum objects, preparation of exotic quantum states, and multi-beam laser machining.
pySLM2 is a python package designed for holographic beam shaping applications, encompassing
hologram generation, simulation, and hardware controls.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Preserving a qubit during state-destroying operations on an adjacent qubit at a few micrometers distance</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2024-motlakunta-preserving-a-qubit-crosstalk-paper/</link><pubDate>Sat, 03 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2024-motlakunta-preserving-a-qubit-crosstalk-paper/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt; Protecting qubits from accidental measurements is essential
for controlled quantum operations, especially during state-destroying measurements
or resets on adjacent qubits, in protocols like quantum error correction.
Current methods to preserve atomic qubits against such disturbances waste coherence time,
extra qubits, and introduce additional errors. We demonstrate the feasibility of in-situ state-reset
and state-measurement of trapped ions, achieving &amp;gt;99.9% fidelity in preserving an ‘asset’ ion-qubit
while a neighboring ‘process’ qubit is reset, and &amp;gt;99.6% preservation fidelity while applying a
detection beam for 11 μs on the same neighbor at a distance of 6 μm. This is achieved through precise
wavefront control of addressing optical beams and using a single ion as both a quantum sensor for
optical aberrations and an intensity probe with &amp;gt;50 dB dynamic range. Our demonstrations advance
quantum processors, enhancing speed and capabilities for tasks like quantum simulations of
dissipation and measurement-driven phases, and implementing error correction.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Programmable XY-type couplings through parallel spin-dependent forces on the same trapped ion motional modes</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2023-kotibhaskar-xy-paper/</link><pubDate>Mon, 08 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2023-kotibhaskar-xy-paper/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt; We propose and experimentally demonstrate an analog scheme for generating XY-type (Jx XX + Jy YY) Hamiltonians on trapped ion spins with independent control over the Jx and Jy terms. The Ising-type interactions σixσjx and σiyσjy are simultaneously generated by employing two spin-dependent forces operating in parallel on the same set of normal modes. We analytically calculate the region of validity of this scheme, and provide numerical and experimental validation with 171Yb+ ions. This scheme inherits the programmability and scalability of the Ising-type interactions with trapped ions that have been explored in numerous quantum simulation experiments. Our approach extends the capabilities of existing trapped ion quantum simulators to access a large class of spin Hamiltonians relevant for exploring exotic quantum phases such as superfluidity and spin liquids.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Microgram BaCl_2 Ablation Targets for Trapped Ion Experiments</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2024-greenberg-microgram-ablation-paper/</link><pubDate>Thu, 18 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2024-greenberg-microgram-ablation-paper/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt; Trapped ions for quantum information processing has been an area of intense study due to the extraordinarily high
fidelity operations that have been reported experimentally. Specifically, barium trapped ions have been shown to have
exceptional state-preparation and measurement (SPAM) fidelities. The 133Ba+ (I=1/2) isotope in particular is a promising candidate
for large-scale quantum computing experiments. However, a major pitfall with this isotope is that it is radioactive and
is thus generally used in microgram quantities to satisfy safety regulations. We describe a new method for creating microgram
barium chloride (BaCl_2) ablation targets for use in trapped ion experiments and compare our procedure to previous methods. We outline
two recipes for fabrication of ablation targets that increase the production of neutral atoms for isotope-selective loading of barium ions.
We show that heat-treatment of the ablation targets greatly increases the consistency at which neutral atoms can be produced
and we characterize the uniformity of these targets using trap-independent techniques such as energy dispersive x-ray spectroscopy (EDS)
and neutral fluorescence collection. Our comparison between fabrication techniques and demonstration of consistent neutral fluorescence
paves a path towards reliable loading of 133Ba+ in surface traps and opens opportunities for scalable quantum computing with this isotope.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Investigations of 2D ion crystals in a hybrid optical cavity trap for quantum information processing</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2023-sun-2d-ions/</link><pubDate>Thu, 21 Mar 2024 20:00:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2023-sun-2d-ions/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt; We numerically investigate a hybrid trapping architecture for 2D ion crystals using static electrode voltages and
optical cavity fields for in-plane and out-of-plane confinements, respectively. By studying the stability of 2D crystals against
2D-3D structural phase transitions, we identify the necessary trapping parameters for ytterbium ions. Multiple equilibrium
configurations for 2D crystals are possible, and we analyze their stability by estimating potential barriers between them.
We find that scattering to anti-trapping states limits the trapping lifetime, which is consistent with recent experiments employing
other optical trapping architectures. These 2D ion crystals offer an excellent platform for quantum simulation of frustrated spin systems,
benefiting from their 2D triangular lattice structure and phonon-mediated spin-spin interactions. Quantum information processing with tens
of ions is feasible in this scheme with current technologies.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>A guided light system for agile individual addressing of Ba+ qubits with 1E-4 level intensity crosstalk</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2023-binai-motlagh2023-a-guided-light-system/</link><pubDate>Thu, 27 Jul 2023 20:00:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2023-binai-motlagh2023-a-guided-light-system/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt; Trapped ions are one of the leading platforms for quantum information processing, exhibiting the highest gate and measurement fidelities of all contending hardware. In order to realize a universal quantum computer with trapped ions, independent and parallel control over the state of each qubit is necessary. The manipulation of individual qubit states in an ion chain via stimulated Raman transitions generally requires light focused on individual ions. In this manuscript, we present a novel, guided-light individual addressing system for hyperfine Ba+ qubits. The system takes advantage of laser-written waveguide technology, enabled by the atomic structure of Ba+, allowing the use of visible light to drive Raman transitions. Such waveguides define the spatial mode of light, suppressing aberrations that would have otherwise accumulated in a free-space optics set up. As a result, we demonstrate a nearest neighbour relative intensity crosstalk on the order of 10&lt;sup&gt;−4&lt;/sup&gt;, without any active aberration compensation. This is comparable to or better than other previous demonstrations of individual addressing. At the same time, our modular approach provides independent and agile control over the amplitude, frequency, and phase of each channel; combining the strengths of previous implementations.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Ion Trap Long-Range XY Model for Quantum State Transfer and Optimal Spatial Search</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2022-lewis-bose-ion-trap-long-range-xy-model-for-quantum-state-transfer-and-optimal-spatial/</link><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2022-lewis-bose-ion-trap-long-range-xy-model-for-quantum-state-transfer-and-optimal-spatial/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt; Linear ion trap chains are a promising platform for quantum computation and simulation. The XY
model with long-range interactions can be implemented with a single side-band Mølmer-Sørensen
scheme, giving interactions that decay as 1/r^α
, where α parameterises the interaction range. Lower
α leads to longer range interactions, allowing faster long-range gate operations for quantum computing. However, decreasing α causes an increased generation of coherent phonons and appears to
dephase the effective XY interaction model. We characterise and show how to correct for this effect
completely, allowing lower α interactions to be coherently implemented. Ion trap chains are thus
shown to be a viable platform for spatial quantum search in optimal O(√N) time, for N ions. Finally, we introduce a O(√N) quantum state transfer protocol, with a qubit encoding that maintains a high fidelity&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Fast and high-yield fabrication of axially symmetric ion-trap needle electrodes via two step electrochemical etching</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2023-kotibhaskar-fast-and-high-yield-fabrication/</link><pubDate>Tue, 14 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2023-kotibhaskar-fast-and-high-yield-fabrication/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt; Despite the progress in building sophisticated microfabricated ion traps, Paul traps employing needle electrodes retain
their significance due to the simplicity of fabrication while producing high-quality systems suitable for quantum information processing, atomic clocks etc. For low noise operations such as minimizing ‘excess micromotion’, needles
should be geometrically straight and aligned precisely with respect to each other. Self-terminated electrochemical etching, previously employed for fabricating ion trap needle electrodes employs a sensitive and time-consuming technique
resulting in a low success rate of usable electrodes. Here we demonstrate an etching technique for quick fabrication of
straight and symmetric needles with a high success rate and a simple apparatus with reduced sensitivity to alignment
imperfections. The novelty of our technique comes from using a two-step approach employing turbulent etching for
fast shaping and slow etching/polishing for subsequent surface finish and tip cleaning. Using this technique, needle
electrodes for an ion-trap can be fabricated within a day, significantly reducing the setup time for a new apparatus. The
needles fabricated via this technique have been used in our ion-trap to achieve trapping lifetimes of several months.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Limits on atomic qubit control from laser noise</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2021-day-limits-on-atomic-qubit-control-from-laser-noise/</link><pubDate>Mon, 27 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2021-day-limits-on-atomic-qubit-control-from-laser-noise/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;This manuscript presents a numerical analysis of the impact of laser noise on qubit operations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt; Technical noise present in laser systems can limit their ability to perform high fidelity quantum control of atomic qubits. The ultimate fidelity floor for atomic qubits driven with laser radiation is due to spontaneous emission from excited energy levels. The goal is to suppress the technical noise from the laser source to below the spontaneous emission floor such that it is no longer a limiting factor. It has been shown that the spectral structure of control noise can have a large influence on achievable control fidelities, while prior studies of laser noise contributions have been restricted to noise magnitudes. Here, we study the unique spectral structure of laser noise and introduce a new metric that determines when a stabilised laser source has been optimised for quantum control of atomic qubits. We find requirements on stabilisation bandwidths that can be orders of magnitude higher than those required to simply narrow the linewidth of a laser. We introduce a new metric, the χ-separation line, that provides a tool for the study and engineering of laser sources for quantum control of atomic qubits below the spontaneous emission floor.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Simulating a measurement-induced phase transition for trapped ion circuits</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2021-czichek-mpt/</link><pubDate>Fri, 03 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2021-czichek-mpt/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;In this theoretical proposal, we describe a hybrid circuit where coherent time evolution is interrupted by sparse projective measurements. A measurement-driven phase transition between volume-law and area-law entanglement is predicted at a specific rate of measurement. Proof-of-principle experiments can be performed in modern trapped ion quantum information processors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt; The rise of programmable quantum devices has motivated the exploration of circuit models which could realize novel physics. A promising candidate is a class of hybrid circuits, where entangling
unitary dynamics compete with disentangling measurements. Novel phase transitions between different
entanglement regimes have been identified in their dynamical states, with universal properties
hinting at unexplored critical phenomena. Trapped ion hardware is a leading contender for the
experimental realization of such physics, which requires not only traditional two-qubit entangling
gates, but a constant rate of local measurements accurately addressed throughout the circuit. Recent
progress in engineering high-precision optical addressing of individual ions makes preparing a
constant rate of measurements throughout a unitary circuit feasible. Using tensor network simulations,
we show that the resulting class of hybrid circuits, prepared with native gates, exhibits a
volume-law to area-law transition in the entanglement entropy. This displays universal hallmarks
of a measurement-induced phase transition. Our simulations are able to characterize the critical
exponents using circuit sizes with tens of qubits and thousands of gates. We argue that this transition
should be robust against additional sources of experimental noise expected in modern trapped
ion hardware, and will rather be limited by statistical requirements on post selection. Our work
highlights the powerful role that tensor network simulations can play in advancing the theoretical
and experimental frontiers of critical phenomena.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Manipulating phonons of a trapped-ion system using optical tweezers</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2021-teoh-manipulating-phonons-of-a-trapped-ion-system-using-optical-tweezers/</link><pubDate>Thu, 19 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2021-teoh-manipulating-phonons-of-a-trapped-ion-system-using-optical-tweezers/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Conventional radio-frequency ion traps provide limited controls over the confining potential. In this manuscript, we theoretically and numerically investigate a hybrid trapping architecture by incorporating optical tweezers (laser beams tightly focused on individual ions) in a conventional trap. The local control over the potential would offer many capabilities - such as engineering a target set of phonon modes, fixing the motional de-coupling problem in a multi-species ion system, and allowing novel experiments in quantum thermodynamics. In the context of multi-species ion systems, optical tweezers would enable efficient sympathetic cooling and faster logic gates between species by taking control over the participation of ions in the collective phonon modes.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Programming the full stack of an open-access quantum computer</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2021-frey-quala-full-stack-programming-quantumion/</link><pubDate>Fri, 11 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2021-frey-quala-full-stack-programming-quantumion/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;This manuscript describes the full stack programming of QuantumION, an open-access, remote-controlled, trapped-ion quantum information processor for the research community, currently being developed at Waterloo. QuantumION is a joint initiative with Prof. Crystal Senko&amp;rsquo;s research group and funded by Canada First Research Excellence Fund (CFREF).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt; We present a new quantum programming language
called ‘Quala’ that enables true full-stack programming of quantum
hardware. Quala allows seamless integration of abstraction
layers such as the digital circuit layer and the analog control pulse
waveform layer. Additionally, the language supports user-issued
low-level hardware instructions like FPGA actions. Mid-circuit
measurements and branching decision logic support real-time,
adaptive programs. This flexibility allows users to write code for
everything from quantum error correction to analog quantum
simulation. The combination of a user-facing calibration database
and a powerful symbolic algebra framework provides users with
an unprecedented level of expressiveness and transparency. We
display the salient characteristics of the language structure and
describe how the accompanying compiler can translate programs
written in any abstraction layer into precisely timed hardware
commands. We intend for this language to bridge the gap
between circuit-level programming and physical operations on
real hardware while maintaining full transparency in each level
of the stack. This eliminates the need for “behind-the-scenes”
compilation and provides users with insights into the day-to-day
calibration routines.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Reprogrammable and high-precision holographic optical addressing of trapped ions for scalable quantum control</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2021-shih-dmd-paper/</link><pubDate>Thu, 08 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2021-shih-dmd-paper/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;We demonstrate programmable, holographic optical addressing of trapped Yb&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; at &lt;em&gt;λ&lt;/em&gt;=369 nm. Using the ion as a sensor, we characterize the total optical aberrations in the entire beam path. We then compensate for the aberration by feeding back onto the hologram, such that the residual aberration at the ion is about &lt;em&gt;λ&lt;/em&gt;/20, which is smaller than specifications for individual commercial optic. Using an iterative Fourier transform algorithm to generate the holograms, we can suppress relative intensity `crosstalk&amp;rsquo; errors to below &amp;lt; 10&lt;sup&gt;−4&lt;/sup&gt; at a few micrometers away while addressing arbitrary sets of ions. Our results are among the highest quality optical addressing of trapped ions.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Programmable Quantum Simulations of Spin Systems with Trapped Ions</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2020-programmable-quantum-simulations-of-spin-systems-with-trapped-ions/</link><pubDate>Wed, 07 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2020-programmable-quantum-simulations-of-spin-systems-with-trapped-ions/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;This is a comprehensive review article on trapped-ion quantum simulation of spin systems, written jointly with colleagues from Univ. of Maryland, UCLA, Tsinghua Univ., Colorado School of Mines, Middlebury College, Rice Univ., Indiana Univ., Univ. of Waterloo, and UC Berkeley. The article should be accessible to a beginning graduate student. We give an overview of quantum simulation of non-trivial spin Hamiltonians generated by programmable interactions between trapped ion spins, adiabatic and dynamical evolution, ground state spin order and propagation of correlations in a many-body system. We cite examples from experiments performed over the last decade with two to fifty three ion spins.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Machine learning design of a trapped-ion quantum spin simulator</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2020-machine-learning-design-of-a-trapped-ion-quantum-spin-simulator/</link><pubDate>Tue, 21 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2020-machine-learning-design-of-a-trapped-ion-quantum-spin-simulator/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Trapped ion quantum simulators can in principle simulate an arbitrarily connected spin model. This requires precise programming of the ions with laser beams. In this paper, we numerically show that modern machine learning methods can be employed to program a trapped ion quantum simulator to simulate spin Hamiltonians on an arbitrary lattice geometry. This work is a collaboration with Prof. Roger Melko&amp;rsquo;s group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt; Trapped ions have emerged as one of the highest quality platforms for the
quantum simulation of interacting spin models of interest to various fields of
physics. In such simulators, two effective spins can be made to interact with
arbitrary strengths by coupling to the collective vibrational or phonon states
of ions, controlled by precisely tuned laser beams. However, the task of
determining laser control parameters required for a given spin-spin interaction
graph is a type of inverse problem, which can be highly mathematically complex.
In this paper, we adapt a modern machine learning technique developed for
similar inverse problems to the task of finding the laser control parameters
for a number of interaction graphs. We demonstrate that typical graphs, forming
regular lattices of interest to physicists, can easily be produced for up to 50
ions using a single GPU workstation. The scaling of the machine learning method
suggests that this can be expanded to hundreds of ions with moderate additional
computational effort.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Dynamical Hamiltonian engineering of 2D rectangular lattices in a one-dimensional ion chain</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2019-dynamic-hamiltonian-engineering-of-2d-rectangular-lattices-in-a-one-dimensional-ion-chain/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2019-dynamic-hamiltonian-engineering-of-2d-rectangular-lattices-in-a-one-dimensional-ion-chain/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;In this publication, we theoretically and numerically demonstrate a powerful analog-digital hybrid quantum simulation protocol that can be used to simulate spin-dynamics on a two dimensional lattice using a linear chain of ions. The simulation protocol makes use of native long range interactions between trapped ion spins, that are then digitally modified to achieve the target spin-spin interaction graph. On one hand, the hybrid simulation scheme is more flexible and requires less experimental control over individual ions than an analog quantum simulation, where the Hamiltonian is simulated by fine-tuning the control parameters. On the other hand, the hybrid simulation scheme does not build the entire time evolution out of quantum logic gates, unlike a fully digital quantum simulator, and therefore is more robust against Trotterization errors. This work is performed in collaboration with researchers from University of California, Berkeley and Army Research Laboratory, Maryland.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>