<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Previous Work on QUANTUM INFORMATION WITH TRAPPED IONS</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/tags/previous-work/</link><description>Recent content in Previous Work on QUANTUM INFORMATION WITH TRAPPED IONS</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 25 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/tags/previous-work/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Single-Atom Heat Machines Enabled by Energy Quantization</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2018-single-atom-heat-machines-enabled-by-energy-quantization/</link><pubDate>Wed, 25 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2018-single-atom-heat-machines-enabled-by-energy-quantization/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Quantization of energy is a quintessential characteristic of quantum systems.
Here we analyze its effects on the operation of Otto cycle heat machines and
show that energy quantization alone may alter and increase machine performance
in terms of output power, efficiency, and even operation mode. Our results
demonstrate that quantum thermodynamics enable the realization of classically
inconceivable Otto machines, such as those with an incompressible working
fluid. We propose to measure these effects experimentally using a laser-cooled
trapped ion as a microscopic heat machine.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Ultra-precise holographic beam shaping for microscopic quantum control</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2016-ultra-precise-holographic-beam-shaping-for-microscopic-quantum-control/</link><pubDate>Tue, 14 Jun 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2016-ultra-precise-holographic-beam-shaping-for-microscopic-quantum-control/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;High-resolution addressing of individual ultracold atoms, trapped ions or
solid state emitters allows for exquisite control in quantum optics
experiments. This becomes possible through large aperture magnifying optics
that project microscopic light patterns with diffraction limited performance.
We use programmable amplitude holograms generated on a digital micromirror
device to create arbitrary microscopic beam shapes with full phase and
amplitude control. The system self-corrects for aberrations of up to several
$\lambda$ and reduces them to $\lambda/50$, leading to light patterns with a
precision on the $10^{-4}$ level. We demonstrate aberration-compensated beam
shaping in an optical lattice experiment and perform single-site addressing in
a quantum gas microscope for $^{87}$Rb.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Measuring entanglement entropy in a quantum many-body system</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2015-measuring-entanglement-entropy-in-a-quantum-many-body-system/</link><pubDate>Wed, 02 Dec 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2015-measuring-entanglement-entropy-in-a-quantum-many-body-system/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Entanglement is one of the most intriguing features of quantum mechanics. It
describes non-local correlations between quantum objects, and is at the heart
of quantum information sciences. Entanglement is rapidly gaining prominence in
diverse fields ranging from condensed matter to quantum gravity. Despite this
generality, measuring entanglement remains challenging. This is especially true
in systems of interacting delocalized particles, for which a direct
experimental measurement of spatial entanglement has been elusive. Here, we
measure entanglement in such a system of itinerant particles using quantum
interference of many-body twins. Leveraging our single-site resolved control of
ultra-cold bosonic atoms in optical lattices, we prepare and interfere two
identical copies of a many-body state. This enables us to directly measure
quantum purity, Renyi entanglement entropy, and mutual information. These
experiments pave the way for using entanglement to characterize quantum phases
and dynamics of strongly-correlated many-body systems.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Strongly correlated quantum walks in optical lattices</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2015-strongly-correlated-quantum-walks-in-optical-lattices/</link><pubDate>Thu, 12 Mar 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2015-strongly-correlated-quantum-walks-in-optical-lattices/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Full control over the dynamics of interacting, indistinguishable quantum
particles is an important prerequisite for the experimental study of strongly
correlated quantum matter and the implementation of high-fidelity quantum
information processing. Here we demonstrate such control over the quantum walk&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the quantum mechanical analogue of the classical random walk - in the strong
interaction regime. Using interacting bosonic atoms in an optical lattice, we
directly observe fundamental effects such as the emergence of correlations in
two-particle quantum walks, as well as strongly correlated Bloch oscillations
in tilted optical lattices. Our approach can be scaled to larger systems,
greatly extending the class of problems accessible via quantum walks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description></item><item><title>Beat note stabilization of mode-locked lasers for quantum information processing</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2014-beat-note-stabilization-of-mode-locked-lasers-for-quantum-information-processing/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 Jun 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2014-beat-note-stabilization-of-mode-locked-lasers-for-quantum-information-processing/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;We stabilize a chosen radiofrequency beat note between two optical fields
derived from the same mode-locked laser pulse train, in order to coherently
manipulate quantum information. This scheme does not require access or active
stabilization of the laser repetition rate. We implement and characterize this
external lock, in the context of two-photon stimulated Raman transitions
between the hyperfine ground states of trapped 171-Yb+ quantum bits.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Quantum Catalysis of Magnetic Phase Transitions in a Quantum Simulator</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2013-quantum-catalysis-of-magnetic-phase-transitions-in-a-quantum-simulator/</link><pubDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2013-quantum-catalysis-of-magnetic-phase-transitions-in-a-quantum-simulator/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;We control quantum fluctuations to create the ground state magnetic phases of
a classical Ising model with a tunable longitudinal magnetic field using a
system of 6 to 10 atomic ion spins. Due to the long-range Ising interactions,
the various ground state spin configurations are separated by multiple
first-order phase transitions, which in our zero temperature system cannot be
driven by thermal fluctuations. We instead use a transverse magnetic field as a
quantum catalyst to observe the first steps of the complete fractal devil&amp;rsquo;s
staircase, which emerges in the thermodynamic limit and can be mapped to a
large number of many-body and energy-optimization problems.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Emergence and Frustration of Magnetism with Variable-Range Interactions in a Quantum Simulator</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2013-emergence-and-frustration-of-magnetic-order-with-variable-range-interactions-in-a-trapped-ion-quantum-simulator/</link><pubDate>Fri, 03 May 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2013-emergence-and-frustration-of-magnetic-order-with-variable-range-interactions-in-a-trapped-ion-quantum-simulator/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Frustration, or the competition between interacting components of a network,
is often responsible for the complexity of many body systems, from social and
neural networks to protein folding and magnetism. In quantum magnetic systems,
frustration arises naturally from competing spin-spin interactions given by the
geometry of the spin lattice or by the presence of long-range antiferromagnetic
couplings. Frustrated magnetism is a hallmark of poorly understood systems such
as quantum spin liquids, spin glasses and spin ices, whose ground states are
massively degenerate and can carry high degrees of quantum entanglement. The
controlled study of frustrated magnetism in materials is hampered by short
dynamical time scales and the presence of impurities, while numerical modeling
is generally intractable when dealing with dynamics beyond N~30 particles.
Alternatively, a quantum simulator can be exploited to directly engineer
prescribed frustrated interactions between controlled quantum systems, and
several small-scale experiments have moved in this direction. In this article,
we perform a quantum simulation of a long-range antiferromagnetic quantum Ising
model with a transverse field, on a crystal of up to N = 16 trapped Yb+ atoms.
We directly control the amount of frustration by continuously tuning the range
of interaction and directly measure spin correlation functions and their
dynamics through spatially-resolved spin detection. We find a pronounced
dependence of the magnetic order on the amount of frustration, and extract
signatures of quantum coherence in the resulting phases.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Quantum simulation of spin models on an arbitrary lattice with trapped ions</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2012-korenblit-quantum-simulation-of-spin-models-on-an-arbitrary-lattice-with-trapped-ions/</link><pubDate>Thu, 27 Sep 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2012-korenblit-quantum-simulation-of-spin-models-on-an-arbitrary-lattice-with-trapped-ions/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;A collection of trapped atomic ions represents one of the most attractive platforms for the quantum simulation of interacting spin networks and quantum magnetism. Spin-dependent optical dipole forces applied to an ion crystal create long-range effective spin–spin interactions and allow the simulation of spin Hamiltonians that possess nontrivial phases and dynamics. Here we show how the appropriate design of laser fields can provide for arbitrary multidimensional spin–spin interaction graphs even for the case of a linear spatial array of ions. This scheme uses currently available trap technology and is scalable to levels where the classical methods of simulation are intractable.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Onset of a quantum phase transition with a trapped ion quantum simulator</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2011-onset-of-a-quantum-phase-transition-with-a-trapped-ion-quantum-simulator/</link><pubDate>Tue, 05 Jul 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2011-onset-of-a-quantum-phase-transition-with-a-trapped-ion-quantum-simulator/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;A quantum simulator is a well controlled quantum system that can simulate the
behavior of another quantum system which may require exponentially large
classical computing resources to understand otherwise. In the 1980s, Feynman
proposed the use of quantum logic gates on a standard controllable quantum
system to efficiently simulate the behavior of a model Hamiltonian. Recent
experiments using trapped ions and neutral atoms have realized quantum
simulation of Ising model in presence of external magnetic fields, and showed
almost arbitrary control in generating non-trivial Ising coupling patterns.
Here we use laser-cooled trapped 171-Yb+ ions to simulate the emergence of
magnetism in a system of interacting spins by implementing a fully-connected
non-uniform ferromagnetic Ising model in a transverse magnetic field. To link
this quantum simulation to condensed matter physics, we measure scalable
correlation functions and order parameters appropriate for the description of
larger systems, such as various moments of the magnetization. By increasing the
Ising coupling strengths compared with the external field, the crossover from
paramagnetism to ferromagnetic order sharpens as the system is scaled up from N
= 2 to 9 trapped ion spins. This points toward the onset of a quantum phase
transition that should become infinitely sharp as the system approaches the
macroscopic scale. We compare the measured ground state order to theory, which
may become intractable for non-uniform Ising couplings as the number of spins
grows beyond 20- 30 and even NP complete for a fully-connected frustrated Ising
model, making this experiment an important benchmark for large-scale quantum
simulation.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Quantum simulation and phase diagram of the transverse-field Ising model with three atomic spins</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2010-edwards-quantum-simulation-and-phase-diagram-of-the-transverse-field-ising-model-with-three-atomic-spins/</link><pubDate>Fri, 27 Aug 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2010-edwards-quantum-simulation-and-phase-diagram-of-the-transverse-field-ising-model-with-three-atomic-spins/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;We perform a quantum simulation of the Ising model with a transverse field using a collection of three trapped atomic ion spins. By adiabatically manipulating the Hamiltonian, we directly probe the ground state for a wide range of fields and form of the Ising couplings, leading to a phase diagram of magnetic order in this microscopic system. The technique is scalable to much larger numbers of trapped ion spins, where phase transitions approaching the thermodynamic limit can be studied in cases where theory becomes intractable.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Quantum simulation of frustrated Ising spins with trapped ions</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2010-quantum-simulation-of-frustrated-ising-spins-with-trapped-ions/</link><pubDate>Thu, 03 Jun 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2010-quantum-simulation-of-frustrated-ising-spins-with-trapped-ions/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Laser-cooled and trapped atomic ions form an ideal standard for the
simulation of interacting quantum spin models. Effective spins are represented
by appropriate internal energy levels within each ion, and the spins can be
measured with near-perfect efficiency using state-dependent fluorescence
techniques. By applying optical fields that exert optical dipole forces on the
ions, their Coulomb interaction can be modulated in ways that give rise to
long-range and tunable spin-spin interactions that can be reconfigured by
shaping the spectrum and pattern of the laser fields. Here we review the
theoretical mapping of atomic ions to interacting spin systems, the
experimental preparation of complex equilibrium states, and the study of
dynamical processes of this many-body interacting quantum system. The use of
such quantum simulators for studying spin models may inform our understanding
of exotic quantum materials and shed light on interacting quantum systems that
cannot be modeled with conventional computers.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Entanglement and Tunable Spin-Spin Couplings between Trapped Ions Using Multiple Transverse Modes</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2009-entanglement-and-tunable-spin-spin-couplings-between-trapped-ions-using-multiple-transverse-modes/</link><pubDate>Wed, 16 Sep 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2009-entanglement-and-tunable-spin-spin-couplings-between-trapped-ions-using-multiple-transverse-modes/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;We demonstrate tunable spin-spin couplings between trapped atomic ions,
mediated by laser forces on multiple transverse collective modes of motion. A
$\sigma_x \sigma_x$-type Ising interaction is realized between quantum bits
stored in the ground hyperfine clock states of Yb ions. We demonstrate
entangling gates and tailor the spin-spin couplings with two and three trapped
ions. The use of closely-spaced transverse modes provides a new class of
interactions relevant to quantum computing and simulation with large
collections of ions in a single crystal.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Large-scale quantum computation in an anharmonic linear ion trap</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2009-large-scale-quantum-computation-in-an-anharmonic-linear-ion-trap/</link><pubDate>Sat, 27 Jun 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2009-large-scale-quantum-computation-in-an-anharmonic-linear-ion-trap/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;We propose a large-scale quantum computer architecture by stabilizing a
single large linear ion chain in a very simple trap geometry. By confining ions
in an anharmonic linear trap with nearly uniform spacing between ions, we show
that high-fidelity quantum gates can be realized in large linear ion crystals
under the Doppler temperature based on coupling to a near-continuum of
transverse motional modes with simple shaped laser pulses.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>