<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Harvard/MIT on QUANTUM INFORMATION WITH TRAPPED IONS</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/tags/harvard/mit/</link><description>Recent content in Harvard/MIT on QUANTUM INFORMATION WITH TRAPPED IONS</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 25 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/tags/harvard/mit/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Single-Atom Heat Machines Enabled by Energy Quantization</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2018-single-atom-heat-machines-enabled-by-energy-quantization/</link><pubDate>Wed, 25 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2018-single-atom-heat-machines-enabled-by-energy-quantization/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Quantization of energy is a quintessential characteristic of quantum systems.
Here we analyze its effects on the operation of Otto cycle heat machines and
show that energy quantization alone may alter and increase machine performance
in terms of output power, efficiency, and even operation mode. Our results
demonstrate that quantum thermodynamics enable the realization of classically
inconceivable Otto machines, such as those with an incompressible working
fluid. We propose to measure these effects experimentally using a laser-cooled
trapped ion as a microscopic heat machine.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Ultra-precise holographic beam shaping for microscopic quantum control</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2016-ultra-precise-holographic-beam-shaping-for-microscopic-quantum-control/</link><pubDate>Tue, 14 Jun 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2016-ultra-precise-holographic-beam-shaping-for-microscopic-quantum-control/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;High-resolution addressing of individual ultracold atoms, trapped ions or
solid state emitters allows for exquisite control in quantum optics
experiments. This becomes possible through large aperture magnifying optics
that project microscopic light patterns with diffraction limited performance.
We use programmable amplitude holograms generated on a digital micromirror
device to create arbitrary microscopic beam shapes with full phase and
amplitude control. The system self-corrects for aberrations of up to several
$\lambda$ and reduces them to $\lambda/50$, leading to light patterns with a
precision on the $10^{-4}$ level. We demonstrate aberration-compensated beam
shaping in an optical lattice experiment and perform single-site addressing in
a quantum gas microscope for $^{87}$Rb.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Measuring entanglement entropy in a quantum many-body system</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2015-measuring-entanglement-entropy-in-a-quantum-many-body-system/</link><pubDate>Wed, 02 Dec 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2015-measuring-entanglement-entropy-in-a-quantum-many-body-system/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Entanglement is one of the most intriguing features of quantum mechanics. It
describes non-local correlations between quantum objects, and is at the heart
of quantum information sciences. Entanglement is rapidly gaining prominence in
diverse fields ranging from condensed matter to quantum gravity. Despite this
generality, measuring entanglement remains challenging. This is especially true
in systems of interacting delocalized particles, for which a direct
experimental measurement of spatial entanglement has been elusive. Here, we
measure entanglement in such a system of itinerant particles using quantum
interference of many-body twins. Leveraging our single-site resolved control of
ultra-cold bosonic atoms in optical lattices, we prepare and interfere two
identical copies of a many-body state. This enables us to directly measure
quantum purity, Renyi entanglement entropy, and mutual information. These
experiments pave the way for using entanglement to characterize quantum phases
and dynamics of strongly-correlated many-body systems.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Strongly correlated quantum walks in optical lattices</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2015-strongly-correlated-quantum-walks-in-optical-lattices/</link><pubDate>Thu, 12 Mar 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/publications/2015-strongly-correlated-quantum-walks-in-optical-lattices/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Full control over the dynamics of interacting, indistinguishable quantum
particles is an important prerequisite for the experimental study of strongly
correlated quantum matter and the implementation of high-fidelity quantum
information processing. Here we demonstrate such control over the quantum walk&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the quantum mechanical analogue of the classical random walk - in the strong
interaction regime. Using interacting bosonic atoms in an optical lattice, we
directly observe fundamental effects such as the emergence of correlations in
two-particle quantum walks, as well as strongly correlated Bloch oscillations
in tilted optical lattices. Our approach can be scaled to larger systems,
greatly extending the class of problems accessible via quantum walks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>