<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Grad on QUANTUM INFORMATION WITH TRAPPED IONS</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/tags/grad/</link><description>Recent content in Grad on QUANTUM INFORMATION WITH TRAPPED IONS</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/tags/grad/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Faizan Samad</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/faizan-samad/</link><pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/faizan-samad/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;I did my BA at UC Berkeley and my MS at the University of Washington. Looking forward to being a member of the team.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Mu Niu</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/mu-niu/</link><pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/mu-niu/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Mu is a PhD student working mostly on the theory of trapped ion and quantum simulation. He enjoys reading novels, playing soccer, and board games in free time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mu is jointly supervised by Dr. Roger Melko.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Dr. Yi Hong Teoh</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/yi-hong-teoh/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/yi-hong-teoh/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Yi Hong was a PhD student working jointly with Prof. Roger Melko and Prof. Rajibul Islam. He works on theoretical aspects of quantum simulation including implementing machine learning methods. Previously, Yi Hong did his MSc thesis with Prof. Islam and Melko, and his PHYS 437 undergraduate thesis with Prof. Islam as well.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Shilpa Mahato</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/shilpa-mahato/</link><pubDate>Thu, 14 Aug 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/shilpa-mahato/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Shilpa is a MSc Physics student in the Department of Physics and Astronomy at the University of Waterloo. She completed her Bachelor of Technology in Engineering Physics from Indian Institute of Technology Dhanbad. She is working on Quantum Simulations Project under Dr. Rajibul&amp;rsquo;s supervision.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Chris Graham</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/chris-graham/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/chris-graham/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Chris completed her undergraduate degree in Physics and Astronomy at the University of Waterloo. She is excited to join the group for her MSc in Fall 2025.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Dr. Nikhil Kotibhaskar</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/nikhil-kotibhaskar/</link><pubDate>Wed, 25 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/nikhil-kotibhaskar/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Nikhil wrote his thesis on programmable XY simulations, precise optical sensing, and building a segmented &amp;lsquo;blade&amp;rsquo; ion trap for quantum simulation. Previously, he co-developed a &amp;lsquo;four-rod&amp;rsquo; ion trap for his MSc thesis in the same group. Nikhil holds an undergraduate degree in Mechatronics from Sastra University in India and worked in the ion trapping lab at the Indian Institute of Science (IISc).&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Hin Pok Cyrus Fung</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/hin-pok-cyrus-fung/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/hin-pok-cyrus-fung/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Cyrus is a graduate student co-supervised by Dr. David Gosset. As an undergrad, Cyrus worked on his PHYS 437 undergraduate thesis with Prof. Islam on &amp;lsquo;Classical Optimization Techniques for a Trapped Ion Quantum Simulator&amp;rsquo;. Cyrus is exploring various optimization and computational techniques to solve problems related to trapped ions, including machine learning.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Sakshee Patil</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/sakshee-patil/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/sakshee-patil/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Sakshee is a graduate student who previously worked with the QSim team as a Research Assistant.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Dr. Chung-You (Gilbert) Shih</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/chung-you-shih/</link><pubDate>Tue, 09 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/chung-you-shih/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Chung-You (Gilbert) did his PhD in the QITI group (2019-23), working on individual optical addressing of trapped ions. Previously, he did his MSc research on holographic beam shaping for quantum simulation in the same group.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Darian Mclaren</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/darian-mclaren/</link><pubDate>Thu, 08 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/darian-mclaren/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;I graduated from Brandon University with a BSc in 2019 with a double major in both mathematics and physics. After taking a year off I started my MMath degree in applied mathematics (with a focus on quantum information) in the fall of 2020.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am jointly supervised by Dr. Joel Wallman, Prof. Rajibul Islam, and Prof. Sivabal Sivaloganathan.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Ali Binai-Motlagh</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/ali-binai-motlagh/</link><pubDate>Mon, 08 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/ali-binai-motlagh/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Ali worked on the QuantumION project (a collaboration with Prof. Crystal Senko&amp;rsquo;s group). His primary controbution was to develop a waveguide-based optical addressing system for individual Barium ion qubits.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Zewen Sun</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/zewen-sun/</link><pubDate>Fri, 31 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/zewen-sun/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Zewen received his BSc degree in physics from Tianjin Normal University and Trent University via a joint program, in 2019. He joined the MSc program at Waterloo in Fall 2019. At Waterloo, Zewen&amp;rsquo;s research interest is in theoretical and numerical investigations on various aspects of light-matter interaction, especially the physics of ions trapped in optical potentials.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Besides physics, Zewen is interested in almost any field, so feel free to talk to him, even if you are not sure what to talk about.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Akimasa Ihara</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/akimasa-ihara/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/akimasa-ihara/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Akimasa is a PhD student under Professor Rajibul Islam&amp;rsquo;s group and is working on QuantumION project. He completed his Bachelor&amp;rsquo;s at Cornell University and has worked with the Oxford Ion Trap Group in the past.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Ali Mustafa Khatai</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/ali-mustafa-khatai/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/ali-mustafa-khatai/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Ali will be joining the QuantumION team as a new Physics MSc student in fall 2023. He obtained his bachelor&amp;rsquo;s degree in Physics and Computer Science from Illinois Wesleyan University.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Fabien Lefebvre</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/fabien-lefebvre/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/fabien-lefebvre/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;I did my undergrad at uOttawa, and I like playing ultimate frisbee and other sports during my free time.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Xinghe Tan</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/xinghe-tan/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/xinghe-tan/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Xinghe (Hawking) is a PhD student on the QuantumION project. He finished his MSc from the same group in Jan 2024. He completed his Bachelor&amp;rsquo;s degree at Queen&amp;rsquo;s University.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Dr. Manas Sajjan</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/manas-sajjan/</link><pubDate>Sun, 30 Aug 2020 22:50:58 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/manas-sajjan/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;I am very interested in the interplay of the quantum and statistical physics at mesoscopic and nanoscopic length scale especially emergence of thermodynamic or statistical irreversibility from reversible quantal dynamics. My PhD was in modelling quantum transport across single molecular junctions, a highly non-equilibrium phenomenon, using electronic structure and convex optimization. Currently, I am invested in exploring the rich frontiers of QI in an AMO physical platform like trapped ions. I was responsible for fabricating the trap electrodes, for making the RF resonator and associated circuitry and for designing the repumping optics all of which were essential for making the first ion-trapping apparatus in the group, a four-rod trap with which we have successfully trapped several ions. Presently I am also dabbling in theoretical proposals for testing quantum fluctuation theorems using hybrid ion traps.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Lewis Hahn</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/lewis-hahn/</link><pubDate>Mon, 03 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/lewis-hahn/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;I enjoy snowboarding any chance I can get.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Jingwen (Monica) Zhu</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/jingwen/</link><pubDate>Sun, 02 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/jingwen/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Jingwen (Monica) received her undergrad education from University of Toronto. She completed her masters on Laser ablation systems for ion loading, and now she explores Floquet systems on the Amethyst machine.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Anthony Vogliano</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/anthony-vogliano/</link><pubDate>Sat, 01 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/anthony-vogliano/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Anthony has worked extensively in QITI lab both on hardware and programming, especially on the main experimental sequences of the Amethyst system. Specific scientific interests include the interplay of coherent dynamics and dissipation, cooling and thermal behavior of many-body quantum systems, and Hamiltonian verification protocols.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anthony enjoys travelling and cooking. His special skills include hand origame, optics table yoga, and having the second longest arms in the lab. Go Bears!&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Nikolay Videnov</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/nikolay-videnov/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/nikolay-videnov/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Nikolay did his MSc thesis on designing an open-source quantum computer (QuantumION) in Prof. Islam&amp;rsquo;s group, and worked as undergraduate co-op students in the same group.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>