<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>ResearchAssoc on QUANTUM INFORMATION WITH TRAPPED IONS</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/tags/researchassoc/</link><description>Recent content in ResearchAssoc on QUANTUM INFORMATION WITH TRAPPED IONS</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 21 Apr 2024 19:19:06 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/tags/researchassoc/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Dr. Mahmood Sabooni</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/mahmood-sabooni/</link><pubDate>Sun, 21 Apr 2024 19:19:06 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/mahmood-sabooni/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Mahmood recently joined our team as a Lead Quantum Processor Engineer, bringing a wealth of experience from his concurrent role at OpenQuantumDesign (ODD). With a background in optical engineering, Mahmood has previously worked on cutting-edge augmented reality projects at Google, demonstrating his expertise in integrating advanced optical technologies.
Since March 2021, Mahmood has been a key member of the QuantumION project, an open-access trapped ion quantum computing facility dedicated to advancing quantum research within the scientific community. His role in this project underscores his commitment to pushing the boundaries of quantum technology.
As an experimental AMO (Atomic, Molecular, and Optical) physicist, Mahmood has made significant contributions to the field of ultracold neutral atoms. At the UQML lab within the Institute for Quantum Computing (IQC), he played a pivotal role in developing exotic quantum systems by working with strongly interacting ultracold quantum matter and light. His work on Rydberg-dressed cavity polaritons is a testament to his innovative approach in quantum system design.
Mahmood&amp;rsquo;s research at UQML focused on employing advanced holographic imaging techniques to individually control and manipulate atoms within optical lattices. This work is crucial for precision quantum experimentation and manipulation. Additionally, he has made notable advancements in quantum memory technology, particularly through the use of naturally trapped rare-earth ions in crystals to store and retrieve quantum information.
Mahmood’s diverse experience and technical expertise will be invaluable as we advance our quantum computing initiatives and explore new frontiers in quantum research.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>