<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>PostDoc on QUANTUM INFORMATION WITH TRAPPED IONS</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/tags/postdoc/</link><description>Recent content in PostDoc on QUANTUM INFORMATION WITH TRAPPED IONS</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 31 Jul 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/tags/postdoc/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Dr. Yu-Ting Chen</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/yu-ting-chen/</link><pubDate>Thu, 31 Jul 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/yu-ting-chen/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Yu-Ting Chen is a Postdoctoral Fellow in the Department of Physics and Astronomy at the University of Waterloo. Her research focuses on quantum simulations with trapped ions. She received her Ph.D. from Harvard University in the Center for Ultracold Atoms, where she developed a platform for cavity quantum electrodynamics with Rydberg atom arrays.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Dr. Sainath Motlakunta</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/sainath-motlakunta/</link><pubDate>Thu, 09 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/sainath-motlakunta/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Sainath was a PhD student (2018-23) in the QITI group developing a &amp;lsquo;blade&amp;rsquo; trap quantum simulator. Previously, he did his MSc thesis from the same group, focusing on analog-digital hybrid quantum simulation protocols.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Dr. Roland Hablützel</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/roland-habl%C3%BCtzel/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 May 2022 20:42:06 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/roland-habl%C3%BCtzel/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Roland joined the QITI group in 2018 to work on the design, construction and characterization of a quantum simulator of spin-lattice geometries based on trapped atomic ions. His research focuses on taking advantage of the shared motional structure of the trapped ions and the flexibility of holographic imaging to program interactions between any pair of spins.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He completed his Ph.D. in the Centre for Quantum Technologies at the National University of Singapore under the supervision of Prof. Dzmitry Matsukevich, where he studied coherent coupling of motional modes in a linear chain of three ions.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Dr. Fereshteh Rajabi</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/fereshteh-rajabi/</link><pubDate>Wed, 30 Jun 2021 23:59:59 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/fereshteh-rajabi/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Fereshteh was a postdoctoral fellow, working on theoretical aspects of trapped-ion physics. She developed hybrid digital-analog quantum simulation protocols, and investigated optical trapping schemes for ions.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Dr. Akbar Jahangiri Jozani</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/akbar-jahangiri-jozani/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/akbar-jahangiri-jozani/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Dr. Akbar Jahangiri works as a Post Doc. for the Quantum ion project.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Dr. Matthew Day</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/matthew-day/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Jul 2020 20:42:06 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/matthew-day/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Since 2019, Matt has been working on QuantumION, an open-access trapped ion quantum computer. He formally joined the QITI group in 2020.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>