<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Alumn on QUANTUM INFORMATION WITH TRAPPED IONS</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/tags/alumn/</link><description>Recent content in Alumn on QUANTUM INFORMATION WITH TRAPPED IONS</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 01 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/tags/alumn/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Dr. Yi Hong Teoh</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/yi-hong-teoh/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/yi-hong-teoh/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Yi Hong was a PhD student working jointly with Prof. Roger Melko and Prof. Rajibul Islam. He works on theoretical aspects of quantum simulation including implementing machine learning methods. Previously, Yi Hong did his MSc thesis with Prof. Islam and Melko, and his PHYS 437 undergraduate thesis with Prof. Islam as well.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Shilpa Mahato</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/shilpa-mahato/</link><pubDate>Thu, 14 Aug 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/shilpa-mahato/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Shilpa is a MSc Physics student in the Department of Physics and Astronomy at the University of Waterloo. She completed her Bachelor of Technology in Engineering Physics from Indian Institute of Technology Dhanbad. She is working on Quantum Simulations Project under Dr. Rajibul&amp;rsquo;s supervision.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Dr. Yu-Ting Chen</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/yu-ting-chen/</link><pubDate>Thu, 31 Jul 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/yu-ting-chen/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Yu-Ting Chen is a Postdoctoral Fellow in the Department of Physics and Astronomy at the University of Waterloo. Her research focuses on quantum simulations with trapped ions. She received her Ph.D. from Harvard University in the Center for Ultracold Atoms, where she developed a platform for cavity quantum electrodynamics with Rydberg atom arrays.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Nathan Rowe</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/nathan-rowe/</link><pubDate>Fri, 09 May 2025 01:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/nathan-rowe/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;I am an undergraduate student studying Mechatronics Engineering. I am working as a Mechanical Designer for the Summer 2025 term.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Oliva Rajguru</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/oliva-rajguru/</link><pubDate>Fri, 09 May 2025 01:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/oliva-rajguru/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;I just finished my third year in physics at the Indian Institute of Science Education and Research (IISER) Mohali, currently a USEQUIP Research Intern at the Institute for Quantum Computing at QITI Lab.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Tal Kaufman</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/tal-kaufman/</link><pubDate>Fri, 09 May 2025 01:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/tal-kaufman/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Tal Kaufman is an undergraduate student studying Mechanical Engineering at the University of Waterloo. He will be working as a part of the QSim group to make progress on the Bloodstone project.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Aryan Sood</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/aryan-sood/</link><pubDate>Fri, 09 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/aryan-sood/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Hello, I am a Aryan Sood and I&amp;rsquo;m in 2nd year Physics and Astronomy. I am a aspiring researcher that is hoping to contribute to Quantum Physics research. With my previous experience as an research assistant in ultra-fast laser optics I hope to be an asset to the the team!&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Zachary Lyu</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/zachary-lyu/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/zachary-lyu/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Mingze (Zachary) Lyu is an undergraduate student currently enrolled in Honours Physics. He will be working with the QSim group as a part-time contractor, as well as conducting his PHYS 437A research project for the Fall 2024 term.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Dr. Sainath Motlakunta</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/sainath-motlakunta/</link><pubDate>Thu, 09 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/sainath-motlakunta/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Sainath was a PhD student (2018-23) in the QITI group developing a &amp;lsquo;blade&amp;rsquo; trap quantum simulator. Previously, he did his MSc thesis from the same group, focusing on analog-digital hybrid quantum simulation protocols.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Kunal Varkekar</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/kunal-varkekar/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/kunal-varkekar/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Purushottam (Kunal) Varkekar is an undergraduate student enrolled in their final year of Astrophysics. He will be working with Dr. Islam and Dr. Sabooni on a Phys 437 research project. The goal of the project is to utilize deformable optics to correct for aberrations in the light and ultimately reduce cross talk when optically addressing a trapped ion system.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Lysistrata Chin Kanellakis</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/lysistrata-chin-kanellakis/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/lysistrata-chin-kanellakis/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Hi, I am Lysistrata Chin Kanellakis and I am a third-year Mechanical Engineering student and I&amp;rsquo;m excited to join the QITI team as a Mechanical co-op student!&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Dr. Nikhil Kotibhaskar</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/nikhil-kotibhaskar/</link><pubDate>Wed, 25 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/nikhil-kotibhaskar/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Nikhil wrote his thesis on programmable XY simulations, precise optical sensing, and building a segmented &amp;lsquo;blade&amp;rsquo; ion trap for quantum simulation. Previously, he co-developed a &amp;lsquo;four-rod&amp;rsquo; ion trap for his MSc thesis in the same group. Nikhil holds an undergraduate degree in Mechatronics from Sastra University in India and worked in the ion trapping lab at the Indian Institute of Science (IISc).&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Abeiku Darkwa</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/abeiku-darkwa/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/abeiku-darkwa/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Abeiku will be working with the QuantumIon project.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Dejan Plavsic</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/dejan-plavsic/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/dejan-plavsic/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Dejan Plavsic is a co-op student here at IQC. He will be working on the mechanical design of the trapped ion system quantum computer. He is excited to contribute to such cutting-edge research and looks forward to collaborating with others.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Gary Zhong</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/gary-zhong/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/gary-zhong/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Gary is a 4th year Mechanical Engineering student studying at the University of Waterloo. He is working with the QITI research group in the Fall 2024 term, focusing on instrumentation design. Gary enjoys exploring the outdoors as well as photography.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Dr. Chung-You (Gilbert) Shih</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/chung-you-shih/</link><pubDate>Tue, 09 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/chung-you-shih/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Chung-You (Gilbert) did his PhD in the QITI group (2019-23), working on individual optical addressing of trapped ions. Previously, he did his MSc research on holographic beam shaping for quantum simulation in the same group.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Taha Malik</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/taha-malik/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/taha-malik/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m a Master&amp;rsquo;s student in engineering with a passion in design. I enjoy playing basketball, photography, and working on my car!&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Leo Xing</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/leo-xing/</link><pubDate>Sun, 30 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/leo-xing/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Leo was an undergraduate mechantronics Co-op student who worked as a mechanical designer in Dr. Islam&amp;rsquo;s group after his Mechatronics Eng. 2A term. Leo worked on a system to stabilize our ion imaging objective lenses.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Mustafa Syed</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/mustafa-syed/</link><pubDate>Sun, 30 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/mustafa-syed/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Mustafa was a co-op student in the Department of Physics and Astronomy. Mustafa built an optical tweezer demo experiment that will be used for teaching undergrad laboratories.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Sanju Sathiyamoorthy</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/sanju-sathiyamoorthy/</link><pubDate>Sun, 30 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/sanju-sathiyamoorthy/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m a multi disciplinary student that is passionate about all things engineering! I love problem-solving, designing and analytical thinking.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Darian Mclaren</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/darian-mclaren/</link><pubDate>Thu, 08 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/darian-mclaren/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;I graduated from Brandon University with a BSc in 2019 with a double major in both mathematics and physics. After taking a year off I started my MMath degree in applied mathematics (with a focus on quantum information) in the fall of 2020.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am jointly supervised by Dr. Joel Wallman, Prof. Rajibul Islam, and Prof. Sivabal Sivaloganathan.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Ali Binai-Motlagh</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/ali-binai-motlagh/</link><pubDate>Mon, 08 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/ali-binai-motlagh/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Ali worked on the QuantumION project (a collaboration with Prof. Crystal Senko&amp;rsquo;s group). His primary controbution was to develop a waveguide-based optical addressing system for individual Barium ion qubits.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Ashley Saggu</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/ashley-saggu/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/ashley-saggu/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Ashley is a second year mechanical engineering student at the University of Waterloo. This term she is working with the QITI group and is interested in using CAD software&amp;rsquo;s and mechanical drawings in a lab environment. She enjoys drawing in her free time and learning new languages.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Ryan Mark</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/ryan-mark/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/ryan-mark/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Ryan is a mechatronics engineering student studying at the University of Waterloo. He will be joining the QITI research group in the Spring 2022 term. He looks forward to bringing his experience from manufacturing and mechanical design to design the optical infrastructure for the quantum simulator. He is excited to be a part of this emerging field and contribute.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In his free time, he enjoys biking, taking photos, and camping.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Souvik Sil</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/souvik-sil/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/souvik-sil/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;I am a student at the university of waterloo, very interested in engineering and physics.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Dr. Roland Hablützel</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/roland-habl%C3%BCtzel/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 May 2022 20:42:06 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/roland-habl%C3%BCtzel/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Roland joined the QITI group in 2018 to work on the design, construction and characterization of a quantum simulator of spin-lattice geometries based on trapped atomic ions. His research focuses on taking advantage of the shared motional structure of the trapped ions and the flexibility of holographic imaging to program interactions between any pair of spins.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He completed his Ph.D. in the Centre for Quantum Technologies at the National University of Singapore under the supervision of Prof. Dzmitry Matsukevich, where he studied coherent coupling of motional modes in a linear chain of three ions.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Alisa Shirkalina</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/alisa-shirkalina/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/alisa-shirkalina/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Alisa is a mechanical engineering student at the University of Waterloo. She is working with the Quantum Simulation team during the winter 2022 term, focusing on mechanical and optical design. Alisa also enjoys rock climbing, skiing, and hiking.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Frank Boal</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/frank-boal/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/frank-boal/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;My name is Frank Boal and I am a 2A Mechatronics student at UW. In my free time I play hockey goalie and am currently playing Jr. hockey locally while attending school.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Mark Wallace</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/mark-wallace/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/mark-wallace/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;After working with the QITI research group in the spring of 2021 I have nothing but positive things to say about my experience. Returning after my 3B Mechanical Engineering school term was one of the easiest choices of my University career! I am looking forward to working on the optics further with more hands on experience and seeing the things designed in terms past come to life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I love digital art and creation as well as film and photography. Material science, coding and mechanical design have been highlights from my coursework and I look forward to applying my existing knowledge while learning as much as possible!&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Stephen Del Grosso Milek</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/stephen-del-grosso-milek/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/stephen-del-grosso-milek/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m currently in my fifth co-op term, employed for the second time with QITI and the QuantumION project. I’m generally interested in the manufacturing and properties of metallic materials, as well as mechanical design techniques. In particular, I’m interested in combinations of cutting-edge machining technology and new iterative design methods to manufacture and create novel creations for fashion and industrial design sectors.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Zewen Sun</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/zewen-sun/</link><pubDate>Fri, 31 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/zewen-sun/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Zewen received his BSc degree in physics from Tianjin Normal University and Trent University via a joint program, in 2019. He joined the MSc program at Waterloo in Fall 2019. At Waterloo, Zewen&amp;rsquo;s research interest is in theoretical and numerical investigations on various aspects of light-matter interaction, especially the physics of ions trapped in optical potentials.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Besides physics, Zewen is interested in almost any field, so feel free to talk to him, even if you are not sure what to talk about.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Gaurav Tathed</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/gaurav-ashish-tathed/</link><pubDate>Thu, 02 Dec 2021 01:42:32 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/gaurav-ashish-tathed/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Gaurav is pursuing Bachelors&amp;rsquo;s Degree in Physics and Astronomy for the University of Waterloo. In the Spring 2020 term, he was working in the QITI group as an undergraduate co-op student. Gaurav is using COMSOL software to investigate noise sources in ion-traps, in particular the thermal effect of radio-frequency voltages on the trapping apparatus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What Gaurav loves about his internship at QITI is how it allows him to learn about ion trapping, and its wide range of applications in different fields ranging from Quantum Computing to High energy physics. Other than physics, Gaurav loves to understand how things work and engineering behind it. For example, as a high school student in India, Gaurav built a CNC plotter using CD players (this project was exhibited in the Nehru Science Center, Mumbai) and an algorithm for traffic signals which uses live time traffic updates. He also likes to sketch and play tennis.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Levi Medeiros</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/levi-medeiros/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/levi-medeiros/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m a coop student working on the QuantomION team. I look forward to learning more about quantum computing and optics design.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Mariah De Torres</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/mariah-de-torres/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/mariah-de-torres/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Mariah De Torres is a Nanotechnology Engineering Undergraduate Student at the University of Waterloo. In Winter 2021, she worked for QITI as a co-op student on the QSim team to design robust optical beam delivery solutions in a trapped-ion quantum simulator. She designed CAD models for beam delivery for short and long-term stability.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Nathan Snider</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/nathan-snider/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/nathan-snider/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Nathan Snider is pursuing a Bachelor&amp;rsquo;s Degree in Mechanical Engineering at the University of Waterloo. Nathan will be working with the QuantumION optics and mechanical team during the Winter 2021 term.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Tim (Jia Hong) Li</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/tim-jia-hong-li/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/tim-jia-hong-li/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Tim is a Mechanical Engineering student at the University of Waterloo. He&amp;rsquo;s working on the QuantumION project during the Fall 2021 term, focusing on mechanical design and optical assembly. Tim likes to learn math, physics, and programming outside of class. Tim also enjoys playing the piano, biking, and photography.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Ziyan Li</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/ziyan-li/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/ziyan-li/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;My name is Jerry and I like food&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Paige Angela Harford</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/paige-angela-harford/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/paige-angela-harford/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Paige is an undergraduate student working in the QSim group, going into her fourth year of Physics at the University of Waterloo. Throughout summer 2021, she will investigate optical table design and fabrication.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Dr. Fereshteh Rajabi</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/fereshteh-rajabi/</link><pubDate>Wed, 30 Jun 2021 23:59:59 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/fereshteh-rajabi/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Fereshteh was a postdoctoral fellow, working on theoretical aspects of trapped-ion physics. She developed hybrid digital-analog quantum simulation protocols, and investigated optical trapping schemes for ions.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Austin Con</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/austin-con/</link><pubDate>Wed, 02 Dec 2020 01:42:32 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/austin-con/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Scott Hubele</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/scott-hubele/</link><pubDate>Wed, 30 Sep 2020 21:16:47 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/scott-hubele/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Scott joined the group for the Summer of 2020 through the IQC Undergraduate Research Award. His projects include simulating photon counts from trapped ion qubits onto multiple detectors to correlate measurements and increase detection fidelity, as well as designing an imaging system which minimizes aberration. He graduated from the University of Alberta in 2020 with a major in Engineering Physics (co-op program) and a minor in Linguistics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Outside of physics, Scott enjoys studying languages, playing the piano, and travelling (but not for now).&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Jakob Devey</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/jakob-devey/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/jakob-devey/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Working on dust trap for his co-op position as a Laboratory Assistant at the University of Waterloo.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Jillian Ryan</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/jillian-ryan/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/jillian-ryan/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Jillian is a 2nd year student in the Physics and Astronomy program at the University of Waterloo. Outside of work she enjoys hiking, reading, and yoga.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Nathaniel Ho-Wah Johnston</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/nathaniel-ho-wah-johnston/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/nathaniel-ho-wah-johnston/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;As part of his co-op placement, Nathaniel will be working on designing hardware and software control for stabilizing experimental parameters such as the intensity of laser beams. He is very interested in the field control systems and is looking forward to his introduction to research on quantum computers.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Qinghao Zhang</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/qinghao-zhang/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/qinghao-zhang/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;For his PHYS 437 BSc Physics project, Qinghao is numerically investigating noise sources in trapped-ion quantum simulations.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Samuel Slavko Laketa</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/samuel-slavko-laketa/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/samuel-slavko-laketa/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;For his PHYS 437 BSc Physics project, Samuel is numerically investigating laser frequency stabilization for trapped-ion quantum information processing. In particular, his interest is in understanding the stabilization of beat-notes in the context of two-photon Raman transitions with mode-locked lasers.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Dr. Manas Sajjan</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/manas-sajjan/</link><pubDate>Sun, 30 Aug 2020 22:50:58 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/manas-sajjan/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;I am very interested in the interplay of the quantum and statistical physics at mesoscopic and nanoscopic length scale especially emergence of thermodynamic or statistical irreversibility from reversible quantal dynamics. My PhD was in modelling quantum transport across single molecular junctions, a highly non-equilibrium phenomenon, using electronic structure and convex optimization. Currently, I am invested in exploring the rich frontiers of QI in an AMO physical platform like trapped ions. I was responsible for fabricating the trap electrodes, for making the RF resonator and associated circuitry and for designing the repumping optics all of which were essential for making the first ion-trapping apparatus in the group, a four-rod trap with which we have successfully trapped several ions. Presently I am also dabbling in theoretical proposals for testing quantum fluctuation theorems using hybrid ion traps.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Rachel DiTommaso</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/rachel-ditommaso/</link><pubDate>Sun, 30 Aug 2020 21:42:32 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/rachel-ditommaso/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Rachel is working on the QuantumION project as an undergraduate co-op student.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Michael Melvin Veenstra</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/michael-veenstra/</link><pubDate>Sun, 30 Aug 2020 21:16:47 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/michael-veenstra/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Michael is an undergraduate co-op student in the QITI lab in Spring 2020. He is in his third year of studying Mechatronics Engineering at the University of Waterloo. In the QITI lab, Michael has been working on electronics projects related to ion trapping.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Outside of work, Michael enjoys soccer, mountain biking, and hands-on projects.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Dr. Matthew Day</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/matthew-day/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Jul 2020 20:42:06 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/matthew-day/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Since 2019, Matt has been working on QuantumION, an open-access trapped ion quantum computer. He formally joined the QITI group in 2020.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Michael Spinazze</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/michael-spinazze/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 21:42:32 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/michael-spinazze/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Sarah Mayer</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/sarah-mayer/</link><pubDate>Sat, 07 Dec 2019 22:01:38 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/sarah-mayer/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Niel Mistry</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/niel-mistry/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 Dec 2019 22:01:37 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/niel-mistry/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Joshua Da Costa</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/joshua-da-costa/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 Dec 2019 22:01:36 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/joshua-da-costa/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Joshua was an undergraduate co-op student in the QITI group for Spring and Fall 2019. His contributions included building radio-frequency amplifier boxes for driving AOMs.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Nikolay Videnov</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/nikolay-videnov/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/nikolay-videnov/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Nikolay did his MSc thesis on designing an open-source quantum computer (QuantumION) in Prof. Islam&amp;rsquo;s group, and worked as undergraduate co-op students in the same group.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Duale Omar</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/duale-omar/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Aug 2019 22:01:35 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/duale-omar/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Natasha Willis</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/natasha-willis/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Apr 2019 22:01:34 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/natasha-willis/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Natasha Willis
Email:
()&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Daniel Francis Julien Neitzert</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/daniel-francis-julien-neitzert/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Apr 2019 22:01:32 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/daniel-francis-julien-neitzert/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Luyao Wang</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/luyao-wang/</link><pubDate>Fri, 07 Dec 2018 22:01:31 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/luyao-wang/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Kaleb Ruscitti</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/kaleb-ruscitti/</link><pubDate>Mon, 30 Apr 2018 22:01:30 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/kaleb-ruscitti/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Kaleb was an undergraduate co-op student in Fall, 2017. He worked on digital light processing devices.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Ilango Maran</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/ilango-maran/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Dec 2017 22:01:29 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/ilango-maran/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Louisa (Ruixue) Huang</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/louisa-huang/</link><pubDate>Mon, 07 Aug 2017 22:01:27 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/louisa-huang/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Jieren Deng</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/jieren-deng/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Aug 2017 22:01:28 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/jieren-deng/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Tony Kappen</title><link>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/tony-kappen/</link><pubDate>Sun, 07 May 2017 22:01:26 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://qiti.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/members/tony-kappen/</guid><description/></item></channel></rss>